<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">devonzuegel.com</title>
  <id>http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml</id>
  <updated>2023-07-11T16:24:29.065000Z</updated>
  <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/" />
  <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <generator>Werkzeug</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">The unconference toolbox</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/the-unconference-toolbox</id>
    <updated>2023-07-11T16:24:29.065000Z</updated>
    <published>2023-07-04T02:43:23Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/the-unconference-toolbox" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="interpersonal" />
    <category term="community" />
    <category term="events" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jasoncbenn&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Jason Benn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;&amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/devonzuegel&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Devon Zuegel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;So, you’ve been invited to an unconference! Maybe you’re not entirely sure what that means (did the organizers misspell &quot;conference&quot;?), or maybe you’ve been to dozens of these before and you’re looking for some ideas for how to run an awesome session.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;This blog post will be a quick primer on what an unconference is, and then we’ll share some tips on how to make a session excellent, both as the host and as a participant.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: rgb(169, 169, 169);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-top: 12px; margin-bottom: -12px&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: rgb(169, 169, 169); font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;TABLE OF CONTENTS:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: rgb(169, 169, 169);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what&quot;&gt;What is an unconference?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#theme&quot;&gt;Selecting a session theme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#formats&quot;&gt;Ideas for session formats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tactics&quot;&gt;Tactics for running a great session&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#failure&quot;&gt;Common failure modes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#attendee&quot;&gt;How to be a great session attendee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#help&quot;&gt;Help us make this doc better!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot; id=&quot;what&quot;&gt;What is an unconference?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Unconferences are participant-driven. &lt;/b&gt;The agenda is created by the attendees when they arrive at the event, and anyone can propose and host a session on a topic they want to discuss. This is in contrast to a typical conference, where the organizers design a schedule of talks and events in advance.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;An unconference is a shared project. &lt;/b&gt;The unconference format is designed to break down the distinction between session hosts and participants. While a conventional conference treats attendees like a passive audience to be entertained by the organizers, the unconference format gives the everyone who attends an opportunity to make the event awesome. By giving each guest ownership over how the time is spent, it turns the event into a shared project. Building things together builds strong relationships, and it can blossom into longer-running collaborations after the event.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Unconferences are choose-your-own-adventure.&lt;/b&gt; At any moment there will be multiple talks happening in parallel, and you can attend whichever one piques your interest. At a typical unconference, a majority of participants will facilitate at least one session.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;The unconference board is the center of the event.&lt;/b&gt; The board is a large grid representing the schedule. The time slots start out blank, and over the course of the unconference, attendees fill them out by proposing sessions. These can change throughout the event as people get to know each other. For example, if you meet someone with complementary expertise, you might consider inviting them to co-host it with you.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse; min-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col style=&quot;width: 419px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 419px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/954839a3-6112-4785-a6d0-21d9eea0c470/f0217436-1d0b-4091-a46e-de6328fb2806.png&quot;  width=&quot;624&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;An example of an unconference board after it has been filled out by the attendees.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot; id=&quot;theme&quot;&gt;Selecting a session theme&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;All topics are fair game at unconferences (unless the organizers specifically state a more narrow theme, of course). Here are a few categories of themes to get your juices flowing:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Your professional expertise&lt;/b&gt; (e.g. mining black holes, how to create real estate pro forma, environmental review regulatory reform)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Something you’re passionate about&lt;/b&gt; (e.g. pottery, quantified self, your experience going through IVF, a standup comedy set)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;A group experience&lt;/b&gt; (e.g. improv, acrylic pouring, cooking class, giant jigsaw puzzle, blind &quot;dining in the dark&quot; dinner, board games, photography workshop)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;A physical activity&lt;/b&gt; (e.g. stretching, group hike, hunting for four leaf clovers, breathing exercises, square dancing.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot; id=&quot;formats&quot;&gt;Ideas for session formats&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;An unconference is an opportunity to mix it up when it comes to format. While conference-style talks can be awesome additions to unconferences too, sessions that take a more interactive or creative approach are where unconferences shine. Here are some ideas for formats that you might consider for your session:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Fireside chat.&lt;/b&gt; An informal conversation between an interviewer and a guest speaker, usually in a cozy setting.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Facilitated group discussion about an important question.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pre-prepared talk + Q&amp;A.&lt;/b&gt; This one is the most similar to what you’ve seen at conferences. To take advantage of an unconference's informality, we encourage you to pause more often for audience reactions or questions.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lightning talks.&lt;/b&gt; You can organize a mini series of short, 5-10 minute presentations on a topic. The series could have a specific theme, or not.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Impromptu panel.&lt;/b&gt; After a round of intros, you pick 2-5 experts and form a panel. You can be moderator, or you can ask one of the experts to ask good questions.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Demo of a new technology. &lt;/b&gt;Brownie points if it's a live demo! But make sure you're prepared so that there aren't lots of awkward gaps.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Live podcast.&lt;/b&gt; Ask another attendee if you can interview them.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Science experiment.&lt;/b&gt; Design an experiment that the group can test together during the session. It doesn’t necessarily have to fit in the 1 hour session; the experiment could run throughout the event and bear results at the end, or possibly even after the unconference is over.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Group brainstorm in a Google Doc. &lt;/b&gt;This is a much higher bandwidth brainstorm format than a single-threaded group conversation. Pose some good questions, ask everyone to type their responses underneath each question, and allow people to comment afterwards. Tip: start by spending 3 minutes &quot;brainstorming ways to brainstorm&quot;, then pick your favorite 2-3 ideas and spend the session on those.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hot seat.&lt;/b&gt; Break into small groups of 3-5 (zoom or IRL), then pick someone to be on the hot seat first. That person chooses a &quot;spicy-ness&quot; level of questions they're comfortable asking. Spicer meaning more vulnerable/personal. For 5 minutes, anyone can jump in and ask questions, one at a time. Switch after 5 minutes. (Thanks to Bhaumik Patel for emailing us this suggestion!) Tips:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Break the ice by going first in front of whole group. Choose the highest spicy level.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Have sample questions people can ask.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;If someone is shy, let them know they can skip any question&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Suggest no more than 1 minute per answer to keep pace going.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot; id=&quot;tactics&quot;&gt;Tactics for running a great session&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Here are some creative facilitation moves that might improve the flow of your session. You don’t need to do all or even any of these. They’re just here to give get your juices flowing as you plan.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ask everyone why they're interested. &lt;/b&gt;&quot;Let's go around and say a sentence or two about any specific questions you'd like me to address.&quot; Good for making a Q&amp;A more targeted to people's curiosities.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Intros.&lt;/b&gt; &quot;Let's go around and say a sentence or two about why you're here and your familiarity with this topic.&quot;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Play with the length of time. &lt;/b&gt;Unconference boards are typically broken down into 1-hour blocks, but that doesn’t mean your session has to be 1 hour! You could take over 2 contiguous time blocks to make a mega 2-hour session, or you could use just 30 minutes if you don’t need the full hour.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Invite specific people to attend your session. &lt;/b&gt;Think about who at the event will have interesting things to add to the discussion and ask them if they’d like to attend your session.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Promote your session in the group chat.&lt;/b&gt; Many unconference organizers will create a group chat for everyone to get announcements throughout the event. 10 minutes before your session starts, you can message the group chat to tell them about your session and who you think would find it interesting.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Invite everyone to sit on the floor. &lt;/b&gt;This can make the session feel more playful and casual. (You can also just remove all of the chairs from the room beforehand, then they will have to sit on the floor!)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Choose an appropriate seating layout. &lt;/b&gt;If you want to encourage interactivity, choose a space where chairs are arranged in a circle. If you want to draw everyone's attention to a speaker or a panel, choose a space where chairs are oriented towards a stage.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bring a physical artifact.&lt;/b&gt; Having a physical object related to what you’re working on can make what you’re talking about more real. You can think of it as grownup show and tell!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Find a cohost.&lt;/b&gt; Think about who might have overlapping/complementary expertise and invite them to run the session with you.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Discuss a topic you’ve written about in depth before.&lt;/b&gt; Some of the best sessions we’ve seen have been writers sharing a quick overview of an essay or book they’ve written, and then giving audience members time for Q&amp;A so the discussion can go beyond what they’ve published publicly. Another variant of this is that you could print out copies of the essay and ask people to read it in silence for the first 5-10 minutes of your session.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Oblique strategies.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://stoney.sb.org/eno/oblique.html&quot;&gt;This set of cards&lt;/a&gt; with cryptic prompts is helpful for breaking creative blocks. Draw a card at random and it might help stimulate new ideas and ways to approach your work.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Create a way for people to keep up the discussion after. &lt;/b&gt;Start a group chat, promote a mailing list, or plan a dinner after the event.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Limit the number of people in your session.&lt;/b&gt; If you want to have a small group discussion, for example, you can tell people &quot;The first 8 people who show up will get to be part of the discussion. If you come after that, you can sit quietly as an audience member&quot; or some variation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ask someone to be the notetaker. &lt;/b&gt;Have them share their notes afterwards with the group or with the rest of the unconference.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot; id=&quot;failure&quot;&gt;Common failure modes&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;The host is under-prepared.&lt;/b&gt; This is the most common failure mode. Although unconferences are designed to be casual, you should still take the role of hosting a session seriously. We've seen amazing sessions that required zero prep, but it's a high variance strategy. A host should at least be able to ask the right questions if a conversation falters.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;The session feels scripted.&lt;/b&gt; Long, non-interactive presentations miss what makes unconferences special. The fix is to encourage group participation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Intros take up the whole session. &lt;/b&gt;Beware the Law of Intro Inflation: that each intro tends to take slightly longer than the previous one. For a group of less than 10 people, intros usually take about 10 minutes. For 10-20 people, you'll need to ask people to keep it to 2 sentences or less. For a large group of 20 or more people, beware, and don’t hesitate to be the Bad Cop!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;A few loud voices dominate the conversation.&lt;/b&gt; A great facilitator is a great host, which means encouraging quiet participants to contribute and being willing to gently interrupt the long-winded.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;The topic goes off the rails.&lt;/b&gt; If your topic degenerates into a debate about capitalism, a great host will find a way to get it back on track.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;The format is over-structured. &lt;/b&gt;We've seen 45 minute sessions with 15 steps (e.g. 1 minute of silent brainstorming, followed by 3 minutes of talking to your neighbors, repeated 4 times, etc). Sometimes this works, but what usually happens is that participants feel like their conversations are repeatedly cut short.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Only a few people show up.&lt;/b&gt; This can often be a feature and not a bug, and pivot to a more intimate, tailored conversation. Sometimes these end up being the best sessions, because they give the small group a chance to go deeper. You can also always cancel the session.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Too many people show up for your format. &lt;/b&gt;The fix depends on the format, but it could involve trying it anyway, pivoting to select an expert panel, dividing the crowd into small groups, etc.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;First-timers don't participate. &lt;/b&gt;Unconferences are wonderfully informal, and you don't need experience to host. If you're shy, try cohosting with another attendee! Alternatively, you can prepare a session and decide after day 1 whether or not to put your session up on the calendar. It can also be encouraging to ask others for their feedback on your topic.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot; id=&quot;attendee&quot;&gt;How to be a great session attendee&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Everyone is responsible for making an unconference great, not just the session host! Here are some ways you can support the host in making each session great: &lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Don’t be afraid to ask questions and add comments&lt;/b&gt;, as long as the host seems they would appreciate it. Unconferences are designed to be more interactive than traditional conferences, and it should be more of a back-and-forth between hosts and participants rather than a performer-audience relationship.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Help the host keep time.&lt;/b&gt; It’s easy to lose track of time, especially when you’re facilitating a great discussion!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Share your own experiences&lt;/b&gt;, though also make sure you’re respecting the host’s intention for the session and not dominating the conversation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Don’t look at your phone!&lt;/b&gt; This one should be obvious, yet somehow it seems not to be…&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot; id=&quot;help&quot;&gt;Help us make this post better!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;-en-paragraph:true;&quot;&gt;Do you have ideas for ho&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;-en-paragraph:true;&quot;&gt;w to create a great&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;-en-paragraph:true;&quot;&gt;unconference experience? Email us at &lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;devonzuegel [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;-en-paragraph:true;&quot;&gt;and &lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;jasoncbenn [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;-en-paragraph:true;&quot;&gt;! We’d love to hear what you've seen work in the wild. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt; .heading {margin-bottom: -8px !important; margin-top: 16px !important; font-weight: 600 !important; font-size: 20px;} .br {height: 0;}  .caption {margin: 0 !important;}   .post .post-content ul li {padding-bottom: 4px; padding-top: 4px;}  .post .post-content ol {margin-left: 26px; !important} .post .post-content ol li {padding-left: 8px}&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">Israel's water miracle</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/israel-s-water-miracle</id>
    <updated>2023-07-01T02:14:39.367000Z</updated>
    <published>2023-07-01T02:14:24Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/israel-s-water-miracle" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="book-notes" />
    <category term="water" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;The saga of Israeli water management is one of the most inspiring stories of the last 75 years. Israel went from having a serious water problem to being a net water exporter to neighboring countries. Meanwhile, the population grew from ~1 million to well over 9 million.&lt;div class=&quot;small-wrap-pull-right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cf8200fb-235f-417d-a147-4a55be480c35/b45a3e3a-2903-4c0c-b58a-2ad579ad14ed.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;With its land mass 60% desert, the region was originally thought to support a max population of just 2 million people. But with tireless work, financial support to find new solutions, and brilliant technological advances, Israel was able to blow past those limits.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;There was no one silver bullet. Israel's water crisis was averted through a portfolio approach. The country invested in a wide range of solutions of varying cost, timelines, and chance of success. Here are a few breakthroughs that were especially powerful:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Drip irrigation:&lt;/span&gt; Israeli engineers invented drip irrigation in the 1960s, replacing traditional flood irrigation. This method saves up to 90% of the water and boosts yields 10-90% (depending on crop type), because it controls water application to match the exact needs of each plant, and it reduces nutrient runoff compared to flood irrigation.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cf8200fb-235f-417d-a147-4a55be480c35/54edc06d-ab98-4500-bf0b-f85ef71438c9.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Desalination:&lt;/span&gt; Israel played a huge role in proving that desalination can be economically viable. The country desalinates 75% of its drinking water from the Mediterranean, and it has built some of the largest and most advanced desalination plants in the world.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cf8200fb-235f-417d-a147-4a55be480c35/97fb5f4e-5368-4d98-a53f-51043a844a82.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Wastewater reuse:&lt;/span&gt; Recycled wastewater is a large and growing source of water in Israel, accounting for &gt;25% of the country's water supply. They reuse &lt;a href=&quot;https://fluencecorp.com/israel-leads-world-in-water-recycling&quot;&gt;90%&lt;/a&gt; of their sewage for agricultural irrigation; for comparison, the US reuses &lt;10%.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cf8200fb-235f-417d-a147-4a55be480c35/c46730e7-2d9a-467f-b216-cd6101310cf4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Improved crop varieties:&lt;/span&gt; Israeli agricultural scientists have developed new crop varieties that are more resistant to heat, drought, and saline conditions.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cf8200fb-235f-417d-a147-4a55be480c35/ca0c9b77-347d-400c-8158-cbb89acde161.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Real pricing:&lt;/span&gt; Most countries subsidize water. For a long time, Israel was no exception. But in 2009, they started charging people for the real price of the water they consumed. Without rationing or limiting supply, real pricing induced households to cut water use by 16%!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cf8200fb-235f-417d-a147-4a55be480c35/0a7ba9ad-82e4-4370-b6e5-dba0fd31dfea.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;If you're interested to learn more, and if you want a spark of hope and a reminder that humans can solve hard problems, I highly recommend reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3r8b84j&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Let There Be Water: Israel's Solution for a Water-Starved World&lt;/a&gt; by Seth Siegel. It put me in such a good mood and was full of interesting technical details too!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cf8200fb-235f-417d-a147-4a55be480c35/3470aa5d-2f16-4e4e-bb23-a20116f086a5.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;img {margin: 12px 0 28px; box-shadow: 0 4px 6px rgba(50, 50, 93, 0.11), 0 1px 3px rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.28) !important;} .small-wrap-pull-right img {margin: 0}&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">America's hidden urban laboratory: the South</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/america-s-hidden-urban-laboratory-the-south</id>
    <updated>2023-06-16T19:28:32.354000Z</updated>
    <published>2023-06-14T18:38:47Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/america-s-hidden-urban-laboratory-the-south" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="usa" />
    <category term="urban-planning" />
    <category term="urban-futurism" />
    <category term="esmeralda" />
    <category term="new-urbanism" />
    <category term="the-south" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;America hasn't built many walkable places in the last few decades, but there are a few exceptions. While collecting &lt;a href=&quot;https://airtable.com/shrvwBRWQxSE7dy4o&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;a list of these special places&lt;/a&gt;, I was shocked to discover that most are in the Southeast. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;My mental image of contemporary southern development did not include an appreciation of urbanism, walkability, and public spaces. On the contrary, it conjured images of massive highways and repetitive suburban sprawl. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;There certainly is a lot of that type of development too, and yet almost all of the best new urban fabric in the last few decades has happened south of the Mason-Dixon line.&lt;div style=&quot;display:none !important&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/d027c6cc-66e6-4271-81cd-f7b2e6ed1251.jpg&quot;  width=&quot;54&quot;/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse; min-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col style=&quot;width: 743px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 743px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/a934d9d8-bd71-4bdf-8b08-e4b9a15b4879.png&quot;  width=&quot;507px&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;A map of New Urbanist villages that &lt;a href=&quot;https://airtable.com/shrvwBRWQxSE7dy4o&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;I've been collecting&lt;/a&gt;. Notice the clusters in South Carolina, Georgia, and the Florida Panhandle.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This clustering in the South makes more sense now that I've studied the question of why the US doesn't build more walkable neighborhoods and towns. The first, obvious answer is that the South generally has less land use regulation than the Northeast and the West Coast, giving real estate developers more latitude in how they build. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;A prime example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnu.org/what-we-do/build-great-places/seaside&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Seaside&lt;/a&gt;, the 80-acre village in Florida that kicked off the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newurbanism.org/newurbanism/principles.html&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;New Urbanism&lt;/a&gt; movement in the early 1980s. The stretch of the Florida Panhandle where Seaside sits was such a backwater that the county didn't even have a Planning Department when Seaside was first getting built! As a result, the creators of Seaside had an incredible amount of freedom to build to their vision.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse; min-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col style=&quot;width: 250px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;col style=&quot;width: 328px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 250px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/249214bd-0e48-413e-b051-ddb4f0c68422.jpg&quot;  style=&quot;--en-naturalWidth:564; --en-naturalHeight:438;&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/9714cbc7-a5f1-434f-a9a1-2af791f2d7c1.jpg&quot;  width=&quot;215px&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 328px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/c1a4fbda-cd72-46fd-a09d-15525710ecf8.jpg&quot;  style=&quot;--en-naturalWidth:428; --en-naturalHeight:640;&quot; width=&quot;196&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 16px&quot;&gt;Seaside, FL was built in the 1980s but feels like a classic small town built before the car. One of my favorite details in Seaside is the secret walking paths winding through each cluster of homes.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;But as I've learned more, I don't think this concentration of new walkable places in the Southeast is just about more open-minded regulation. Notably, even though &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gainesvilleregister.com/opinion/columns/snuggs-all-about-county-zoning/article_41c9975a-6d54-11ea-a2c4-2f66821220c8.html&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Texas bars counties from imposing zoning codes&lt;/a&gt;, Texas doesn't have many of these places (at least that I know of). And yet the development that has been sprouting up all around Texas is rarely mixed-use, even though there is nothing standing in developers' way from a zoning perspective. If the lack of good new walkable places was just a function of restrictive land use policy, you would see more of this type of development in unincorporated parts of Texas counties!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I think another critical factor is that Seaside served as a model of success, which became the seed of a growing community of practice throughout the region. Seaside provided a example for developers and public officials to point at and say, &quot;Wow, that model of development worked out great in the neighboring county. Let's build something like that here, too.&quot; People are much more likely to learn about models of development that are close by rather than across the country, because they're easier to go see in person and it's more likely that someone they know has been there. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Planning departments are risk-averse, and they have lots of reasons to be that way. They get little credit when they approve an unconventional project that the public loves; meanwhile they get an earful if they approve one that the public hates. As a result, having a successful example of a new development model nearby makes it a much easier ask for an official to take a swing at a big idea.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse; min-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col style=&quot;width: 340px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 340px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/8ab5f2a9-6549-4bf3-b2c0-8d89b785e1aa.jpg&quot;  style=&quot;--en-naturalWidth:1500; --en-naturalHeight:521;&quot; width=&quot;599px&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption center&quot;&gt;Fun fact: Seaside was the movie set for &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;The Truman Show&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div&gt;Nearby role models are possibly even more important for developers. One aspect of real estate that I didn't appreciate before is just how driven by comparables the industry is (known in the industry as &quot;comps&quot;). Developers are constantly asking themselves &quot;What other projects in this region have succeeded? Which have failed?&quot; and then shaping their projects to match the successes and avoid the failures. As a result, the industry is very self-referential and self-reinforcing. What gets built today is typically just a slight variation of what got built yesterday. Changing the zoning and building codes is risky, non-deterministic, and political; meanwhile it's much more straightforward to just do what's already been done.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Besides land use regulation, financing projects with debt is another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.astronomy.com/science/the-great-filter-a-possible-solution-to-the-fermi-paradox/&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Great Filter&lt;/a&gt; that kills innovative projects, or at least nudges them in a more conventional direction. Lenders are understandably risk-averse, because they get no upside if the project does spectacularly well. If a developer's bold bet pays off, the lender gets the same amount of money as if it did just ok; meanwhile the lender can lose all of their money if the project fails. As a result, lenders will often insist on making the project as similar as possible to something that they've already seen work. To lenders, boring is a feature not a bug.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The obvious way to avoid this Great Filter is to simply not use debt. However, leveraging a project with debt makes returns much more attractive to equity investors, so it's often necessary to make a project competitive as an investment. If real estate were funded by pure equity rather than debt, I think we would see a lot more experimentation. And indeed, the most innovative real estate projects are often funded by wealthy individuals with deep pockets who don't need to bring on debt to fill out the capital stack. If a project is special enough that it makes for outsized returns even without debt, then it can work out very well for investors in the end too. However, getting that multiple with debt doesn't require innovation in the end product, and thus feels safer to many investors.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Those rare innovative projects that do get built have outsized impact on the industry, because they can prove out a model that more conservative capital can then invest in. Seaside, FL was originally built by a single developer with a crazy idea and a piece of land he already owned, which gave him time and autonomy to build his vision. By contrast, most developers are working on &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;literally&lt;/span&gt; borrowed time, so they don't have the luxury of experimenting with a new model.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;But then once a place like Seaside has proven out a model, then other developers can take those learnings and apply them to projects with more conventional investors and lenders. As Seaside took off, nearby communities popped up along the Florida Panhandle following their playbook, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://alysbeach.com/&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Alys Beach&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.30aescapes.com/rosemary-beach-community&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Rosemary Beach&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.visitsouthwalton.com/neighborhoods/watercolor/&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Watercolor&lt;/a&gt;. Disney also took note of the Seaside model and built &lt;a href=&quot;https://celebrationtowncenter.com/&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Celebration, FL&lt;/a&gt; following many of the same design principles. Developers just over the border in Georgia and South Carolina began to take note too, building beautiful places like &lt;a href=&quot;https://ioncommunity.com/&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;I'On&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newpointsc.com/default.php&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Newpoint&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palmettobluff.com/live/wilson-village&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Palmetto Bluff&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnu.org/publicsquare/2021/05/11/%E2%80%98green-streets%E2%80%99-gentle-density-new-studio-town&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Trillith&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/sherikoones/2019/03/05/serenbe-an-agrihood-community-to-visit-or-stay-forever/?sh=72c71e333f5a&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Serenbe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://habershamsc.com/&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Habersham&lt;/a&gt;, and beyond.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse; min-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col style=&quot;width: 173px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;col style=&quot;width: 172px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 173px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/a2778f08-5a93-412e-8960-7f1144c0b9b1.jpg&quot;  style=&quot;--en-naturalWidth:800; --en-naturalHeight:1106;&quot; width=&quot;168px&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alysbeach.com/&quot;&gt;Alys Beach, Florida&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 172px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/43063daa-9beb-4411-b0f8-d825192df0b7.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.30aescapes.com/rosemary-beach-community&quot;&gt;Rosemary Beach, Florida&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;width: 345px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/d027c6cc-66e6-4271-81cd-f7b2e6ed1251.jpg&quot;  style=&quot;--en-naturalWidth:2500; --en-naturalHeight:1667;&quot; width=&quot;287px&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://habershamsc.com/&quot;&gt;Habersham, South Carolina&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 173px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/bc591fad-02e0-4ca9-bed3-01b8448ca0e4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/sherikoones/2019/03/05/serenbe-an-agrihood-community-to-visit-or-stay-forever/?sh=72c71e333f5a&quot;&gt;Serenbe, Georgia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width: 172px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/4f4d0ed2-1489-4b82-9e61-88a3f032474e/bdd9a02b-0506-4ad6-bd99-4f1c8bd58af0.webp&quot;  style=&quot;--en-naturalWidth:2200; --en-naturalHeight:1388;&quot; width=&quot;299px&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palmettobluff.com/live/wilson-village&quot;&gt;Palmetto Bluff, South Carolina&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;These design patterns, loosely referred to as &quot;New Urbanism&quot;, are slowly spreading from the South into the rest of the country. As you can see from the map at the top of this post, there are some lovely places popping up in &lt;a rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot; href=&quot;https://www.cnu.org/publicsquare/2023/02/06/washington-beach-town-based-northwest-vernacular&quot;&gt;Washington&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot; href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20230502202651/https://www.nytimes.com/2020/10/31/business/culdesac-tempe-phoenix-sprawl.html&quot;&gt;Arizona&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot; href=&quot;https://www.doverkohl.com/southmain&quot;&gt;Colorado&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot; href=&quot;https://www.wheelerdistrict.com/&quot;&gt;Oklahoma&lt;/a&gt;, and beyond (and those are just my count – it's very likely that I'm missing some!). &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;However the South is still the epicenter of this community of practice, and I can count on one hand the number of New Urbanist communities that have been built west of the Mississippi or north of the Mason-Dixon line. If we can show more people that these places are existing and thriving, and expand the community of practice beyond the Southeast, we will see more wonderful places built across America.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;table .caption {margin-top: -2px !important;    line-height: 1.4}    .center {text-align: center !important;}&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;.post .post-content table {margin-top: 16px !important; margin-bottom: 16px !important;}&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;/* Use to make the images bleed past the text */       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;@media (min-width: 1200px) { table {min-width: calc(100% + 190px) !important; margin-right: -90px !important; margin-left: -90px !important}}       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;@media (min-width: 768px) { table { min-width: calc(100% + 140px) !important; margin-right: -70px !important; margin-left: -70px !important}}       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;@media (max-width: 768px) { table tr &gt; * {flex:none !important; width: calc(100% - 12px) !important}}       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">Why do home buyers look at price/sqft more than renters?</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/why-do-home-buyers-look-at-price-sqft-more-than-renters</id>
    <updated>2023-01-09T01:23:27.712000Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-09T01:15:41Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/why-do-home-buyers-look-at-price-sqft-more-than-renters" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="development" />
    <category term="housing" />
    <category term="economics" />
    <category term="real-estate" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;A question that's puzzled me for a while is why home buyers focus on price/sqft so much more than renters. I asked around for what other people thought and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/devonzuegel/status/1611069189078548480&quot;&gt;got some interesting answers&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to write up my takeaways.&lt;div style=&quot;display: none !important&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/585172ff-b756-4d76-a7dc-112bab44384e/bb9fcfa1-90c0-4072-8211-9af70e2c2c05.jpg&quot;  width=&quot;119&quot;/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;I. Investments demand legibility&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Homeownership is an investment &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; consumption good, while renting is just a consumption good. As a result, buyers are forced to think of it in more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/&quot;&gt;legible&lt;/a&gt; ways as opposed to just an amenity bundle.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;For&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;buyers, a house serves as both a personal residence and also an asset that can be sold for a profit later on. As as a result, buyers tend to be more concerned with how the market values the property, and how much it might be worth when it comes time to sell.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The mechanics of buying and selling homes basically force you to consider price/sqft:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;When you sell, the realtor you hire will figure out how much it can sell for buy looking at &quot;comps&quot;, comparisons to similar properties that have sold in the area.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;When you buy, the bank will determine how much to lend you based on an appraisal, which in turn is done in terms of comps and price/sqft.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Realtors, banks, institutional investors, and appraisers do this because they need a way to understand where the house sits as fungible asset among the market. Price/sqft makes a home more abstract and fungible, enabling them to boil down a unique asset to a small set of dimensions that can be sorted in a spreadsheet.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Renters generally care only about how much they personally value the property, rather than its long-term value or how others will perceive its value. They are focused on finding a place that meets their immediate needs and budget and tend to think about a property as a total amenity bundle: how many bedrooms/bathrooms, how close to work, whether there's a balcony, how nice the kitchen is, etc. They do care about spaciousness, but it's one of many aspects of the property that they look at.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;II. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Owners renovate more than renters&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Homebuyers see square footage as a blank canvas that can be transformed to fit their needs and preferences, while renters are less able or willing to renovate their space. Landlords tend to be conservative about how much a tenant can change their space, so having extra square footage that's poorly used doesn't add much value to the renter. Even if the landlord is open to the tenant modifying the unit, renters are less motivated to invest as much in renovations since the value goes back to the landlord rather than to the renters themselves.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Side note: This dynamic is totally different in commercial leasing. In that context, tenant buildout and modification of the space is often taken as a given, and the price/sqft is often the headline advertised number. When the market is soft, commercial lease negotiations can even include concessions from the landlord to pay for some of the improvements chosen by the tenant.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;III. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Sqft is less accurate for rentals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Square footage is a more reliable metric for measuring the usable space of single-family houses, whose layouts tend to have fewer constraints. It is not as accurate for measuring the usable space of rental units because they tend to have more irregular floor plans. This is especially true for apartments, which may have odd shapes or unusable space due to the need to fit a large number of units into a small area or because they are located in a converted building. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;IV. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Rentals rarely list &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;square footage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;, while sales listings almost always do&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Another reason why renters might pay less attention to price/sqft is because rental listings rarely list it. Meanwhile, sale listings almost always include price/sqft. Of course the causality may run the other way – maybe the listings don't include those metrics because people don't care – but I'm sure that if landlords started highlighting price/sqft, renters would pay marginally more attention to those metrics.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;V. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Renters are more likely in survival mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;People who are just trying to survive are more likely to rent than to buy, because they tend to have less access to capital and cash flow. This means they are going for whatever they can afford, not trying to optimize. Meanwhile buyers are considering between different investments. Buyers also likely have more options to begin with, and metrics like price/sqft are only really useful as a comparison point between multiple options.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;heading&quot;&gt;VI. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Renting just isn't as important a decision as buying&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;The simplest answer might just be that renting just isn't such a big deal, while buying a home is often the single biggest financial decision a person will make in their their life. Renting is typically just a 6-18 month lease, while buying ties you to the asset until you can sell. As a result, you just don't take the decision as seriously and thus look at fewer metrics.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;People are even less likely to look at the price/sqft of a hotel rooms, because it's a much lower impact decision in the first place if you're only there for a few days. Some renters know the price/sqft, but I've never heard of any travelers cite the nightly price/sqft of a hotel room.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#a9a9a9&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 12px;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 12px; color: rgb(169, 169, 169); font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Thanks to everyone who responded to my Twitter thread, especially &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://constructionphysics.substack.com/&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 12px; color: rgb(169, 169, 169); font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Brian Potter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 12px; color: rgb(169, 169, 169); font-style: italic;&quot;&gt; for spending extra time talking me through some of these ideas.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt; .heading {margin-bottom: -8px !important; margin-top: 6px !important; font-weight: 600 !important; font-size: 20px;}    &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">Numbers for understanding cities</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/numbers-for-understanding-cities</id>
    <updated>2022-09-19T17:57:26.576000Z</updated>
    <published>2022-09-19T17:49:45Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/numbers-for-understanding-cities" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="statistics" />
    <category term="cities" />
    <category term="tools-for-thought" />
    <category term="spreadsheet" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;Whenever I think about physical places, I find myself coming back to a few types of numbers again and again.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I've collected these into spreadsheets so that I can reference them more easily, and I figured they might be useful to others too:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1QqawtnslJsM10s4t5bEURYYS_9rwu4RxVYgAOl__PLw/edit#gid=0&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Urban densities&lt;/a&gt; – Population density in various cities around the world&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/f8a044f4-e361-4255-a117-fb32441ca0a7/46d51f0e-6304-4fa2-9708-8db5753fc1b3.png&quot;  width=&quot;312&quot;/&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1RgXEUsUM_qgCjIPyubWrzuWS0wpRoZNBR67lMtUgviE/edit#gid=1623210591&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Wharton Residential Land Use Regulatory Index 2018&lt;/a&gt; – How restrictive is land use policy in nearly 3,000 municipalities across the USA? (Does not include unincorporated areas)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/f8a044f4-e361-4255-a117-fb32441ca0a7/96e7c9f3-423e-4376-b9e1-9700757af6b5.png&quot;  width=&quot;369&quot;/&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1RgXEUsUM_qgCjIPyubWrzuWS0wpRoZNBR67lMtUgviE/edit#gid=1712339702&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Freedom in the 50 States&lt;/a&gt; – Comparison of various measures of freedom in each US state. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freedominthe50states.org/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/f8a044f4-e361-4255-a117-fb32441ca0a7/d1210f18-b268-4827-b013-bba9e342479b.png&quot;  width=&quot;367&quot;/&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapdevelopers.com/area_finder.php&quot;&gt;Area calculator&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/b&gt;– Find the area of a shape you draw on a Google Map&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/f8a044f4-e361-4255-a117-fb32441ca0a7/81b2ad6e-becf-4eba-8e2f-edf2ef14c8a8.png&quot;  width=&quot;424&quot;/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I'll add more datasets to this list as I think of them. 🙂&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;.post .post-content ol li img { margin-top: 8px;   margin-bottom: 20px;   border: 1px solid rgb(50 50 93 / 11%); }&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">Inside Argentina's currency exchange black markets</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/inside-argentina-s-currency-exchange-black-markets</id>
    <updated>2022-09-10T15:12:10.227000Z</updated>
    <published>2022-09-10T03:08:00Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/inside-argentina-s-currency-exchange-black-markets" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="crypto" />
    <category term="economics" />
    <category term="argentina" />
    <category term="latin-america" />
    <category term="inflation" />
    <category term="currency" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;In Argentina, your money is worth double if you skip the airport currency exchange and instead go to one of the many black market exchanges hidden throughout Buenos Aires.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;These illegal exchanges are called &quot;cuevas&quot; (the word for &quot;cave&quot; in Spanish), and they are a crucial part of Argentina's financial infrastructure. Argentinians are constantly exchanging their pesos (ARS) for other currencies, usually US dollars (USD), and back again because they simply cannot rely on their country's fiat currency. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;The value of ARS is infamously unstable. The country's money supply has persistently high inflation, punctuated by bouts of hyperinflation. Argentina has seen an &lt;a href=&quot;https://english.elpais.com/usa/2021-03-05/argentinas-perpetual-crisis.html#:~:text=Since%201921%2C%20when%20it%20was,peso%20ley%20from%201970%20to&quot;&gt;average of 100% annual inflation for the last century&lt;/a&gt;. In 1989, inflation reached 3,000%!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;The government has also imposed strict capital controls that make moving money in and out of the country challenging. It is impossible to take USD out of Argentinian ATMs, even as an American with a US bank account.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Argentinians who vacation in Costa Rica or pay their child's college tuition in Miami have to pay exorbitant taxes to move money out of the country, or sometimes cannot move the money at all. As a result, these sorts of transactions require an illegal workaround.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;ARS has a pegged exchange rate, meaning its value is not set by market demand like USD but rather is set by government mandate — and the pegged exchange rate almost always overstates the value of the peso. As a result, there is a thriving black market that sets a floating, informal exchange rate called &lt;a href=&quot;https://bluedollar.net/informal-rate/&quot;&gt;Dólar Blue&lt;/a&gt;. These two rates are often dramatically different: as of early 2022, the official ARS to USD exchange rate is 110 to 1, while the informal is 215 to 1. If you bring $1 USD to a legal exchange, you get just 110 ARS pesos, whereas you’ll get 215 ARS pesos in return for that same dollar at a cueva.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;As a result of these challenges, there is a lot of demand to move money around without the government’s visibility. Illegal money movement is so common that it's discussed as openly and casually as people in the US might discuss what bank they use.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;This backdrop makes Argentina a &lt;a href=&quot;https://restofworld.org/2022/why-crypto-crash-different-latin-america/&quot;&gt;poster child for cryptocurrencies&lt;/a&gt;. The argument from crypto proponents is that Argentinians have personally experienced the problems of centralized fiat currency for generations, so they're especially receptive to the case for decentralized currencies that their government cannot meddle with.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Crypto enthusiasts are correct in many ways. I know an Argentinian grandma who barely uses a computer, yet as soon as she heard about Bitcoin from her grandson in 2016, she instantly said &quot;Money the government can't touch? Help me buy it right now,&quot; and she's been holding it ever since. (An understandable reaction when you've seen your country go through &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argentine_peso&quot;&gt;5 different currencies in your lifetime&lt;/a&gt;.) &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I've also seen firsthand how crypto has transformed the way the black market operates in Argentina. When I first started visiting the country on a yearly basis in 2018, cuevas generally only advertised exchange rates between ARS and other fiat currencies, such as USD and the euro (EUR). Now, they've added the exchange rates between BTC, ETH, TRON, and other cryptocurrencies to the menu because more and more of their customers are demanding it.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;However, the specific ways crypto is used in Argentina are quite different from how many people who are building out the crypto ecosystem originally imagined it. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;For example, crypto enthusiasts often imagine a world where individuals control their own wallets directly — storing the cryptographic code on their local computers or phones, not using a third party, like MetaMask.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;But the reality on the ground is quite different: Argentinian crypto users use intermediaries and centralized apps to access crypto. This is especially striking given the reasons Argentinians use crypto in the first place, which you’d expect to make them especially receptive to the value proposition of decentralization. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The peso lost almost all its value in a generation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;If you'd saved $100,000 USD worth of pesos in 1995, they would be worth about $310 USD today. In the mid 1990s, 1 ARS = $1 USD; as of July 2022, the value is 322 ARS = $1 USD. Anyone who held onto pesos in that time would have had their life savings obliterated. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Argentinians have learned that it's much better to save in other countries' currencies, and the favorite for decades has been USD, particularly in the form of $100 bills. In 1995, a paper from the Federal Reserve &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/econres/ifdp/dollarization-in-argentina.htm&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; that &quot;Argentina has received as much as $40 billion in net shipments of U.S. currency, or well over $1,000 per capita,&quot; and the number has likely only increased since then.&lt;div class=&quot;medium-wrap-pull-right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/cd22ee2a-ef98-46f5-ad43-c9782615825d/9ff52af7-74f2-4b39-9138-5b50e4d973bd.jpg&quot;  width=&quot;108&quot;/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Argentinians have also learned to not trust banks, even with accounts denominated in other currencies. In 2001-2002, the government enacted something called &quot;el corralito&quot;, shutting Argentinians' access to their bank accounts for almost a year. When they could finally extract money again, they found that (a) their USD deposits had to be exchanged for pesos and (b) pesos had lost 2/3 of their value. The lesson the Argentines learned was that they couldn't trust banks or any other government-regulated financial services, because at any moment the government could just stop them from accessing their money.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I've seen more $100 dollar bills in Argentina than I've seen in my entire lifetime in the US. $100 bills make up 80% of all US currency by value and 34% of all bills in circulation, according to &lt;a href=&quot;http://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/34778/1/MPRA_paper_34778.pdf&quot;&gt;economist Edgar Feige&lt;/a&gt;, and there are more &quot;Benjamins&quot; floating around than all of the $5 and $10 notes combined. This is unintuitive to most Americans – $100 bills are a rare sighting, at least for me. This is not unintuitive to Argentinians, whose family has probably saved stacks of $100 bills under mattresses for generations. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Bricks — actual bricks, not stacks of cash — are another common savings mechanism, especially for working-class Argentinians. The value of bricks is fairly stable, and they're useful to a family building out their house. Argentina doesn't have a mortgage industry, and thus buying a pallet of bricks each time you get a paycheck is an effective way to pay for your home in installments. (Bricks aren't fully monetized, in that I don't think people buy bricks and then sell them later, so people only use this method of saving when they actually have something they want to use the bricks for.)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;As you can imagine, there are challenges that come with saving in wads of $100 bills or stacks of bricks. For one thing, they take up a lot of space. Worse, your life savings are also at constant risk of theft, damage, and fire. If something does happen, the bills are not insured or protected by any institution; they’re just gone. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;As a result, Argentinians are interested in alternatives for storing their money, especially those that are both out of the clutches of their government and safer than storing piles of cash at home.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Crypto is starting to make it easier for Argentinians to save&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;In the US, critics often make fun of crypto enthusiasts by pointing out that if you store your crypto on a hardware wallet and then lose the disk or the password, you're hosed. They scoff at crypto’s volatility and difficult user experience. They rightfully point out that most Americans won't make this tradeoff when institutions like banks can store the money for them securely, and without risk of losing the money. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The tradeoffs are very different in Argentina: when your alternative is storing boxes of money in the attic or under your mattress, an unobtrusive hardware wallet sounds like a pretty good idea. Instead of carrying around suitcases of cash when you want to buy a house, you can just carry a USB stick with your private key to complete the transaction. When reflecting on crypto’s volatility, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://restofworld.org/2022/why-crypto-crash-different-latin-america&quot;&gt;common sentiment&lt;/a&gt; is &quot;I would rather have a digital asset whose price goes up and down than a currency whose only real trend is down.&quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;When most people think of crypto, they tend to think of bitcoin (BTC) and Ethereum (ETH). However, these are not ideal savings instruments because they are highly volatile and the transaction fees remain expensive. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;As a result, BTC and ETH are not so common for daily use in Argentina. Stablecoins such as USD-T, USD-C, and TRON are a more popular solution because they are pegged to a more stable currency (usually, USD).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Notably, the stablecoins popular for savings are also much more centralized. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yahoo.com/video/tether-blocks-160-million-usdt-152718550.html#:~:text=Because%20Tether%20is%20a%20centralized,listing%20them%20on%20the%20blacklist.&quot;&gt;The Tether Foundation (which issues USD-T) has blocked transactions&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptonews.com/news/risks-of-centralized-stablecoins-materialize-as-100k-usdc-fr-7067.htm&quot;&gt;so has the Centre consortium (which issues USD-C)&lt;/a&gt;. While TRON is technically not centralized, &lt;a href=&quot;https://coinmarketcap.com/alexandria/article/how-decentralized-are-decentralized-networks#:~:text=Consequently%2C%20co%2Dfounder%20Chen%20(,re%2Delected%20every%20six%20hours.&quot;&gt;its cofounder has said that its architecture is not as decentralized as other blockchains’&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;They are attractive to Argentinians because they are not under the control of the government, not because they are decentralized and truly permissionless.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Remote work is a way to decouple from the local economy&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;At the same time that crypto is changing how people use money, remote work is becoming increasingly common for Argentinians, because it allows them to earn in other currencies besides the peso. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Remote workers sometimes set up bank accounts abroad so they don't have to bring them back into Argentina (and thus under the watchful eye of the government). They hold funds in places like Payoneer, PayPal, Mercury, or Estonian and US bank accounts, and withdraw just enough in Argentina to pay for the day-to-day expenses. Sometimes these are set up legally, and sometimes they are not.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;USD and EUR have historically been the most popular currencies for remote work, in part because most of the remote jobs come from the US or Europe, and in part because those currencies are quite stable and accepted worldwide. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;However, overseas accounts remain out of reach for many people — setting up bank accounts abroad generally requires traveling there, which is expensive and time-consuming. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Crypto is starting to help a small but growing number of remote workers in Argentina. Crypto allows them to move their money around from within Argentina, rather than having to use an intermediary in another country. This can save them trips to Estonia, the US, or wherever they would’ve had to open their bank accounts. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;If done covertly, it can also allow them to avoid Argentinian taxes (though this also requires coordination with their employer, which many employers are not willing to do, because it increases their liability). &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Argentinians who use crypto are increasingly untethered from the local Argentinian economy and increasingly plugged into the global cloud economy. Crypto is providing new solutions to problems that Argentina has faced for generations, and many Argentinians are excited about its potential to make it easier and safer to make, use, and store money.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Crypto is more practical than cash for many transactions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;Distrust of the formal financial system is part of everyday life in Argentina. On every payday, the first stop many Argentinians make is to the cuevas (the illegal money exchanges), where they can swap their ARS for USD. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;This solves one problem — they’re no longer holding onto the hot potato that is the Argentine peso — but creates many other problems.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;For one, stacks of bills are difficult to transport. This increases the energy cost necessary for any transaction. For example, an American friend of mine considered buying an apartment in Buenos Aires many years ago, but he balked when he realized he’d have to stuff a suitcase with $100 bills and fly them to Argentina in order to meet the seller’s expectations. He decided it was not worth the hassle.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;It’s also dangerous to transport physical bills. Criminals know that people often carry cash, which makes muggings more attractive in Argentina compared to countries where most transactions are done on credit cards. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The cuevas themselves have serious security problems, too — they have to transport sometimes millions of dollars in USD to and from their offices every day, so they end up having to move the location of their offices often so that other criminals don’t catch wind of where their couriers will be going in and out of their operation. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Crypto is starting to help Argentinians deal with these problems. When making a big purchase, like a house, you can just carry a USB stick with your private key to complete the transaction, instead of having to transport suitcases full of cash. Like with cash, the government doesn't have to be the wiser that the crypto transaction occurred, enabling buyers and sellers to avoid capital controls and taxes. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;From talking to locals, it sounds like this is still rare, in part because both sides of the transaction have to agree to doing it in crypto. It also requires a high level of technical comfort, user experience is poor, and volatility is high. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;However, Argentinians have a lot of experience finding gaps in complex systems and then taking advantage of them fully, so I expect adoption to grow rapidly as word spreads that this is possible.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Another problem with cash is it may require a trusted third party that both the buyer and seller are comfortable with to hold the funds in escrow. Because many of these transactions are under the table, participants have little recourse if things go wrong, so it’s crucial that the third party is trustworthy. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Smart contracts, programmed on the blockchain, have the potential to take out this third party and instead allow the buyer and seller to use a neutral contract that holds funds in escrow until both sides have agreed the transaction is complete. I’ve yet to hear of an Argentinian who’s done this, but it’s a big opportunity to solve a major problem in the ecosystem.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Crypto has also become central to the cuevas’ business&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;The cuevas I spoke to said that crypto has made it much safer and cheaper to transfer large sums of money on the backend.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;One key use case is to evade the government’s capital controls so that they can bring money in and out of Argentina. The government has made it impossible to extract USD from ATMs (yes, even if you're an American with an American bank account denominated in USD), so historically a major way that USD bills entered the country was through the crossing the physical border between Argentina and Uruguay. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Uruguay is Argentina’s much more economically free neighbor, and it doesn't have restrictions on USD, so there has been a large flow of dollars across the river between the two countries. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;However, this was expensive and risky, since the cuevas had to smuggle large quantities of physical cash across the wide Rio de la Plata river. Crypto, especially USD-C and USD-T, has made it much easier to move that money around: now, the cuevas can move dollars in and out of the country from their highrise offices in Buenos Aires, rather than having to get onto a boat.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Another use is to pay someone in USD (usually in a stablecoin) in exchange for physical pesos. This is especially true for the &quot;wholesalers&quot; called &quot;cuevas mayoristas,&quot; who are responsible for delivering large amounts of cash to smaller retail cuevas. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Historically, these wholesalers have had motorcycle couriers who biked all around the city delivering stacks of pesos or dollars to smaller cuevas around town. These couriers wear custom-made vests tucked under their coats that are specially designed to carry the maximum number of bills without looking visibly bulky, to avoid the attention of law enforcement and criminals who might realize that a juicy payday is tucked into every nook and cranny around their chest and legs. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Crypto has helped reduce this risk by giving the cuevas a way to move USD around without having to physically transport it on humans, who are prone to getting robbed. These couriers are still an important part of the business because Argentina is mostly a cash economy and thus people still need their physical pesos, but crypto has reduced the risk of loss dramatically by reducing the number of dollars they need to carry alongside the pesos.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Most Argentinians interact with crypto through intermediaries&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;From talking to several cuevas and to my Argentinian friends, it sounds like it’s still uncommon for a typical person to use crypto to move money around directly. More likely, they go to a cueva and the cueva does the transaction for them, and the person doesn’t realize that the cueva was using crypto behind the scenes to do it.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I find this fascinating because one of the big assumptions of crypto proponents was that when crypto is adopted widely, everyone will control their own wallets and addresses. But in Argentina right now, it’s more common for consumers to interact with a centralized business that itself depends on the decentralization of crypto to exist, rather than for the consumers to interact with the blockchain directly. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Another way to look at it is that the cuevas’ use of crypto on the backend enables people to more easily access dollars and other assets, even if they aren't interacting with crypto directly themselves.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;In practice, this may end up having similar effects as the world where every person has their own hardware wallet because if the centralized cueva they depend on misbehaves or goes under, the decentralization of the blockchain that the cueva uses allows the end customer to just move over to another centralized service that is layered on top of the blockchain. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;But I could also see it working similarly to how we access the internet today. Technically, the internet is a decentralized service that you can connect to without going through an intermediary like Facebook or Google, but in practice almost everyone goes through those giants to access the web, and they layer lots of other centralized services on top that make it very difficult to eject from their ecosystem.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Even cuevas have picked convenience over decentralization&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;It’s also fascinating to see the tools people and cuevas use to interact with crypto. Every cueva manager I met said that they and their customers prefer TRON over BTC or ETH or other more well-known cryptocurrencies, primarily because the transaction fees are so much lower. They said their customers don’t send them crypto that often, but when they do it’s usually TRON from a Binance wallet. They were surprised when my friend tried to send them ETH directly from his wallet.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The fact that they use TRON and Binance was notable, because both of these are centralized services without the best reputations. TRON’s design is technically decentralized, but its cofounder has &lt;a href=&quot;https://coinmarketcap.com/alexandria/article/how-decentralized-are-decentralized-networks&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; it as &quot;centralized&quot; because it depends on such a small number of &lt;a href=&quot;https://cointelegraph.com/blockchain-for-beginners/what-is-tron-trx-and-how-does-it-work-a-beginners-guide&quot;&gt;super representatives&lt;/a&gt;, who are responsible for keeping track of the transaction history in the TRON ecosystem to validate transactions. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Binance, a crypto exchange, is completely centralized, meaning that any balances that anyone has with Binance are stored on a central database that Binance controls, rather than on a permissionless blockchain. This means that Binance can freeze accounts if it chooses to, which sounds an awful lot like the situation the Argentine banking system was in during the 2001 &quot;corralito,&quot; which left millions of Argentinians without access to their savings for nearly a year.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;This ambivalence for decentralized cryptocurrencies isn’t limited to consumers. Of all the cuevas I spoke with, only one actually manages their own keys. Every other cueva I know uses Binance as their primary wallet for crypto, both for day-to-day transfers and for holding their reserves. Many of them are holding hundreds of thousands or even millions of dollars in these reserves, which could easily get shut down at any time since what they’re doing is explicitly illegal.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;This is striking because it doesn't match up with the story that many crypto maximalists push about decentralization. Enthusiasts talk all about how important decentralization is, and given their unfortunate financial history, Argentinians more than most should appreciate those benefits. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;And yet, there they are, holding their reserves in a centralized app that could get shut down tomorrow, theoretically just as easily as the banks were during the 2001 corralito.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The way I explain this to myself, it seems that the key characteristic that draws Argentinians to these relatively centralized cryptocurrencies is that the government doesn't control them, rather than being completely decentralized in a way that no one controls them. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;To me, this is evidence that they are not bought into the philosophy behind crypto, but rather the utility of crypto. And insofar that the utility and philosophy are discordant, the more you'll find that the theories of crypto enthusiasts don't match reality. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The revealed preference of these cuevas is that they care more about convenience than absolute decentralization. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;What makes this so odd is that a lower-risk alternative is fairly straightforward and only slightly more expensive — instead of using TRON through Binance, they could use TRON directly, which would only cost them $0.50 USD per transaction. This might not make sense for individuals moving small amounts of money around, but the cuevas are often storing hundreds of thousands or millions of dollars in reserves in Binance, and so fifty cents on top of transactions of that scale is virtually nothing. It seems like a worthwhile insurance policy to avoid having your money in a centralized institution that is &lt;a href=&quot;https://beincrypto.com/binance-ceo-fights-back-after-craig-wright-claims-the-exchange-is-about-to-implode/&quot;&gt;widely distrusted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Unless I'm missing something, cuevas’ use of Binance seems very short-sighted, especially to store their reserves. My best guess of what’s going on is that they still haven’t learned all of the gotchas involved with crypto, simply because it’s so early. Additionally, the business owners often depend on younger employees to handle &quot;the crypto stuff.&quot; An Argentinian friend of mine jokes that when you ask a cueva to do a crypto transaction, they call to the back of the office and bring out their &quot;crypto guy,&quot; who’s usually like a 17-year-old kid with a smartphone who knows the basics of the Binance app. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I'm curious to see what'll happen if Binance implodes—will the cuevas lose big, and if so, what will they learn? I could see it going one of two ways. On one hand, it might spook them away from crypto in general. On the other hand, it might make them appreciate decentralization more, and teach them that they weren't taking advantage of enough of crypto's unique properties.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;~&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Crypto has quietly transformed the way many Argentinians move money and access the global economy. The volume of transactions going through crypto is &lt;a href=&quot;https://complyadvantage.com/insights/cryptocurrency-transaction-volumes-grow-567-as-focus-turns-to-defi/&quot;&gt;growing rapidly&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s increasingly out of the government’s control. However, the way that has played out is quite different from what many crypto enthusiasts have imagined.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Decentralization is a worthy goal, but in practice it seems that most Argentinians don’t care that much about it, at least not in the way purists talk about it. They’re more worried about whether the government can get their hands on their money; as long as the answer is &quot;no&quot;, they don’t seem to care much about who else has control over it.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;At first, I was surprised to see so many Argentinians using centralized tools to access crypto. But upon reflection, I realized this is exactly what we should expect from human psychology: people implicitly value convenience over preparing for long-tail risks — like the risk of a stablecoin becoming unstable, or an exchange collapsing or being seized by the government — and centralization makes it easier to provide that convenience. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;It’s not until something goes terribly wrong that we start to invest in protecting ourselves from the downside. And plenty has already gone wrong in Argentina’s traditional financial system. So if Argentinians aren’t rushing to embrace decentralized currencies, that says a lot about what we should expect from the rest of the world.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;muted&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic&quot;&gt;This essay was originally published in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freethink.com/technology/crypto-argentina-black-market-cash&quot;&gt;Freethink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; on&lt;/span&gt; August 13, 2022&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;h2 {font-weight: 600 !important;  font-size: 22px !important;}&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">Uncharted waters: what startups can learn from pirates about compensation</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/uncharted-waters-what-startups-can-learn-from-pirates-about-compensation</id>
    <updated>2022-09-10T13:20:27.765000Z</updated>
    <published>2022-09-10T02:37:38Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/uncharted-waters-what-startups-can-learn-from-pirates-about-compensation" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="economics" />
    <category term="pirates" />
    <category term="compensation" />
    <category term="startups" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;Pirate crews developed a surprisingly similar approach to compensation in the 17th century. Just like many startups, they also balanced equity incentives with other mechanisms that would be familiar to a startup employee today, such as bonuses.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;These surprising similarities offer an interesting frame through which we can reflect on why startup equity and bonuses are structured the way they are. We can learn a lot about the theory of compensation in modern companies by looking at how pirates designed incentives to organize and motivate their work.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;It’s called &quot;venture&quot; capital for a reason&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Pirates offered their crew members equal shares of their loot, similar to how many startups offer employees equity in the business. In this way, 17th-century pirates and modern-day startups are more similar to each other than to law-abiding ships or established companies, the most common alternative employment options in their respective eras.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;In the Golden Age of Piracy (late 1600s-early 1700s), it was incredibly rare for law-abiding workers to own a share of a business. Piracy offered one of the few avenues for a normal person to have a chance for great riches and autonomy over their work. Merchant ships and royal navies were the two main alternatives to piracy for employment for sailors, neither of which had any sort of equity-based compensation. They paid flat wages on a per-voyage basis, which meant that no sailors got rich from working on a merchant or navy ship.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;This has persisted through the centuries. To this day, employee ownership still isn’t the norm outside of startups. Just &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20211210130620/https://www.nceo.org/articles/employee-ownership-by-the-numbers&quot;&gt;22% of Americans&lt;/a&gt; who work for a for-profit company report that they own any shares of stock in the company. Meanwhile, it’s common practice for a startup to give equity, and it’s a crucial part of the compensation package to attract talent. Many potential employees won’t even consider working for an early startup that doesn’t offer equity. For example, multiple people in &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/2/https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28561054&quot;&gt;this Hacker News thread&lt;/a&gt; state that they wouldn’t accept a job from an employer like Mailchimp that doesn’t offer equity compensation, and a former Mailchimp employee &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/save/https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28561738&quot;&gt;cited&lt;/a&gt; lack of equity as the &quot;largest factor&quot; in their move.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The crucial similarity between startups and pirates—which they don’t share with most modern companies or with 17th-century merchant ships—is that the teammates themselves are essentially acting as investors, rather than just as employees. Pirates had no base wage and only made money if they captured another ship; meanwhile, early startup employees generally take a pay cut in the short term in return for a stake in the company. In both cases, the teammates are essentially investing their own time into the company at a discount in exchange for potential upside in the future value they are part of creating.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;By contrast, merchant ships and the navy paid low but steady wages. The average law-abiding sailor’s wage was &quot;about $4,000 to $8,800 in current U.S. dollars,&quot; according to Peter T. Leeson. Although these wages were low, it was much less risky than getting paid purely based on a &quot;you eat what you kill&quot; policy. Similarly, many modern workers choose to work for a big company that pays a steady salary instead of a startup where their equity might be worth millions—or might be worthless—down the line.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Although pirates and startup employees both venture into uncharted waters, the risks that pirates faced were of course far greater than anything most startup employees face today.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;In startups, the biggest risk is that your equity might be worthless. A pirate might die, lose a limb, or go to prison for life.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Despite these differences, the essential structure of the risk-reward tradeoff that sailors faced when considering piracy was similar to the choice that modern workers face when deciding between a startup or an established company. The potential for massive upside attracts ambitious, risk-tolerant people to startups today similar to how it attracted them to pirate ships in the 17th century. Luckily, these days there are better employment alternatives than the merchant marine, the royal navy, and piracy!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 18px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Treasure for me but not for thee&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;One of the key challenges that both startups and pirate ships face is that it’s difficult to control (or even measure) how productive a particular teammate is day by day. When management can’t guarantee that you’ll operate for the benefit of the team’s broader goals, they need to design incentives so that you’ll do what’s right for the team even when no one is watching.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;That said, the reason it’s difficult to control or measure a startup employee’s productivity is different from why it’s difficult to do so for a pirate. In a tech company, most employees are doing &quot;knowledge work&quot;. Much of the hard work happens inside of someone’s head, where you can’t see it. When a knowledge worker produces output, it can be almost as much effort to verify that it was done well as it was to produce it in the first place.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Pirate ships have a different challenge with maintaining discipline and quality control: a collective action problem. The most crucial moments that defined a pirate ship’s success were when they attacked another ship to capture their treasure. These are also one of the most dangerous moments, because there is physical violence involved. If you’re a pirate, you want to see your crew successfully capture a merchant ship because it’ll make you rich, but you also want to avoid violence because… well, you might die before you get to see any of that treasure. The resulting incentive is to hold back and let your comrades board the victim ship before you, so that you can get the benefits without the costs. However if all of the pirates do that, the raid is much more likely to fail.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The way pirates solved this problem was similar to how startup compensation works today—although luckily the stakes aren’t so high in a modern Delaware C-corp. Before each journey, pirates would create a written constitution that laid out the base compensation for each crew member, as well as bonuses for especially brave actions. Alexander Exquemelin, a 17th century French pirate surgeon who wrote &lt;span style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;The History of the Buccaneers of America&lt;/span&gt;, described one excerpt of the articles of agreement that governed his ship: &quot;For the loss of a right arm, 600 pieces of eight… for a left arm 500 pieces of eight... If a man lost the use of an arm, he would get as much as if it had been cut off, and a severe internal injury which meant the victim had to have a pipe inserted in his body would receive 500 pieces of eight […] in recompense.&quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3RWTJ6N&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;The Invisible Hook&lt;/a&gt;, Peter T. Leesen describes, &quot;To further encourage full effort, pirate articles contained incentive provisions that paid bonuses to crew members who displayed exceptional courage in battle, were the first to spot potential targets, and so forth, out of the common purse… According to section VIII of Ned Low’s crew’s articles, &quot;He that sees a sail first, shall have the best Pistol or Small Arm aboard of her.&quot; These incentive provisions must have worked well since, as Johnson noted, &quot;It must be observed, they [pirates] keep a good Look-out; for, according to their Articles, he who first espies a Sail, if she proves a Prize, is entitled the best Pair of Pistols on board, over and above his Dividend.&quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The typical startup compensation structure has many similarities with that of a pirate ship, though luckily startup employees are generally not risking life or limb when they join a high-growth company. When an employee has had an exceptional year and goes above and beyond their standard duties, their manager will often award them a cash or stock bonus, significantly increasing their overall compensation.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Bonuses are important to both startup and pirate compensation structures, because they counteract the &quot;rising tides lift all boats&quot; effect that company equity and equally splitting booty both create. While equity and equal shares of booty align individuals with the goals of the overall team, they also allow for free-riders to benefit from the work of others without having to do anything on their own, once they’ve joined the team.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The motivational effect of bonuses shows up in the data too. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hbs.edu/research/pdf/11-041.pdf&quot;&gt;An analysis&lt;/a&gt; from the Yale School of Management studied how sales teams respond to bonus-based compensations plan, and they found that &quot;bonuses enhance productivity [and] overachievement commissions help sustain the high productivity of the best performers even after attaining quotas&quot;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Bonuses also disaggregate individual impact over time, compared to equity whose value is determined by the aggregate impact of the whole team. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gsb.stanford.edu/insights/executive-bonuses-might-work-better-you-think&quot;&gt;Recent research&lt;/a&gt; from the Stanford Graduate School of Business illustrates this effect. The researchers studied data between 2006-2017 for over 1,400 public companies. &quot;They found that tying bonus-related performance to non-bottom-line financials largely helped address issues related to timing: that is, the time lag between when an executive makes an investment in the business’s future and when that investment pays off. If there’s a timing mismatch, boards will sometimes disregard costs of certain investments when calculating bonuses — as a way to encourage investments in projects worth pursuing, especially the kind that are designed to promote long-term growth.&quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Whether it’s for exceeding a KPI or being the first to board a merchant ship, performance-based bonuses incentivize team members to carry their weight and take initiative rather than depending on the enthusiasm or past successes of their coworkers.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;wide-img-wrapper&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/55b89b1e-c76c-4bd4-9031-06b8131b28e3/bba24d48-6abc-4a8b-bd87-89f3cf5a9276.jpg&quot;  width=&quot;121&quot;/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Pirates are a fascinating comparison point for modern startups. If you look closely at how pirates worked together, it’s easy to recognize organizational structures that are alive and well in modern startups.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Although the day-to-day work of a sea bandit couldn’t be more different than that of a frontend engineer at a SaaS startup, the risk-reward tradeoff is very similar. Putting that tradeoff in visceral terms can be a fun way to make it more concrete and intuitive when venturing into uncharted waters.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 12px;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 12px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;muted&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic&quot;&gt;This essay was originally published in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.withcompound.com/uncharted-waters&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 12px;&quot;&gt;Compound Archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 12px;&quot;&gt; on January 14, 2022&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">Buenos Aires recommendations</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/buenos-aires-recommendations</id>
    <updated>2022-03-06T19:37:29.460000Z</updated>
    <published>2022-03-06T19:36:53Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/buenos-aires-recommendations" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="spanish" />
    <category term="travel" />
    <category term="cities" />
    <category term="argentina" />
    <category term="latin-america" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;I wrote a Buenos Aires guide with recommendations and tips for a group of friends I was traveling with in December 2021, and I figured it might be useful to other people too. I adore Buenos Aires and spend about a month each year there, so I'm always thrilled to hear when friends are going to spend time in the city, and I love sharing what I know about the place with newcomers. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Buenos Aires is an underrated city. My friends are often surprised to hear that it's similar to Barcelona, and that several neighborhoods could have come straight out of Paris, if it weren't for the Spanish signs on the shops. Its pasta, pizza, and gelato rival that of any Italian city — people don't realize that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_Argentines&quot;&gt;over 60%&lt;/a&gt; of Argentines have some Italian ancestry, and they kept Italian food traditions alive when they came over to the New World. (Personally, I think Argentinian gelato is even better than Italian gelato...)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Buenos Aires is also very cheap. Of all the places I've been, BsAs has the highest ratio of quality of life to cost of living. A 10-minute taxi ride will cost you 50¢, and a spacious AirBNB in the nicest neighborhoods in the city can cost as little as $20 USD per night. The most expensive meal I've ever had in Argentina came out to $40 USD, and that was at one of the fanciest restaurants in the entire country.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I could gush about Argentina endlessly, but I'll stop there and just point you to the guide I wrote: &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin-top: 0; margin-bottom: 8px&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bolder; border-bottom: 2px solid rgba(54, 125, 162, 0.4) !important&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://devonz.notion.site/PUBLIC-Buenos-Aires-recommendations-b2b23d7a2d9746b7974e11b09ed81aec&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 24px; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;font-size: 24px;&quot;&gt;Buenos Aires guide&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The guide is focused on practical details like COVID tests, how to exchange money, restaurants, and that sort of thing. There are so many interesting things to share about Argentina's culture, monetary system, urban planning, history, and beyond, but those will come in separate posts in the future. In the meantime, you might find &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=from%3Adevonzuegel%20argentina&amp;src=typed_query&amp;f=top&quot;&gt;some of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=from%3Adevonzuegel%20buenos%20aires&amp;src=typed_query&amp;f=top&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=from%3Adevonzuegel%20argentinian&amp;src=typed_query&amp;f=top&quot;&gt;tidbits&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=from%3Adevonzuegel%20bsas&amp;src=typed_query&amp;f=top&quot;&gt;interesting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;I hope you have an amazing time while you're in Argentina!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;table style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse; min-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 185px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 185px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;width: 185px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/ee67f4b3-ce3f-4f5d-bc70-0e57d78b4de2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/7ef726d0-4dad-4418-83b7-3896458c84d0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/7e969303-bef3-43e4-b430-756d0d6ff679.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/eaf59805-a6f6-4c51-b902-95c1fc187664.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;width: 185px; padding: 8px; border: 1px solid;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/0919845c-88c7-46be-8a62-f11c71e8d4df.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/ab165168-e438-4d75-abab-7687206df649.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/521d774d-d255-4d9b-af62-60056a544f6c.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/de4ea41e-961a-45b1-a61e-350216450d63/fd6884fc-d322-4a33-9fd5-244bc9041e5b.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;table .caption {margin-top: 1px !important}    .center {text-align: center !important;}&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;.post .post-content table {margin-top: 16px !important; margin-bottom: 16px !important;}&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;/* Use to make the images bleed past the text */       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;@media (min-width: 1200px) { table {min-width: calc(100% + 190px) !important; margin-right: -90px !important; margin-left: -90px !important}}       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;@media (min-width: 768px) { table { min-width: calc(100% + 140px) !important; margin-right: -70px !important; margin-left: -70px !important}}       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;@media (max-width: 768px) { table tr &gt; * {flex:none !important; width: calc(100% - 12px) !important}}       &lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://devonzuegel.com/feed.xml">
    <title type="text">Field notes: Panamá, SEZs, &amp;amp; biotech</title>
    <id>http://devonzuegel.com/post/field-notes-panama-sezs-biotech</id>
    <updated>2022-02-06T01:41:28.200000Z</updated>
    <published>2022-02-05T22:39:50Z</published>
    <link href="http://devonzuegel.com/post/field-notes-panama-sezs-biotech" />
    <author>
      <name>Devon Zuegel</name>
    </author>
    <category term="travel" />
    <category term="cities" />
    <category term="city-reviews" />
    <category term="startup-cities" />
    <category term="panama" />
    <category term="charter-cities" />
    <category term="latin-america" />
    <category term="stem-cell" />
    <category term="biotech" />
    <category term="field-notes" />
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;I just spent a week in Panamá City, and figured I'd share my observations in case they're useful to anyone else interested in similar questions.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The purpose of the trip was to research locations for a gene therapy/stem cell clinic that my friend is planning to start. I also explored a few of Panamá's Special Economic Zones (SEZs) as part of my ongoing research about &lt;a href=&quot;http://devonzuegel.com/tag/startup-cities&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;startup cities&lt;/a&gt;, as well as to learn about the opportunities they offer for businesses like my friend's clinic.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;The fact that this was a goal-oriented trip actually made it even more fun. I recommend this as a way to organize your travels. For me, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/devonzuegel/status/1489644177084149766&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;travel is most satisfying when I have a concrete goal&lt;/a&gt;—in this case, &quot;where's the best place to open a gene therapy clinic in Central America?&quot;—because it forces you to actually learn about the place rather than take whatever path just happens to be pre-paved for tourists. You bump up against real constraints in the real world, rather than interacting with some manicured narrative of what the place is about. Best yet, you learn about what its future might be, not just the past.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Another reason I was excited to visit Panamá was that I lived in a tiny rural village called El Águila in 2010 as part of a high school exchange program. I hadn't been back in 12 years, so I was excited to reconnect with my host family. It was fascinating and invigorating to see how the country had changed!&lt;div style=&quot;display: none !important&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: rgb(0, 0, 0);&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images.postach.io/0bd25fcc-8ab1-40fe-8eef-bcafaae885c1/55d7a16e-a420-4f9f-a109-5d2ba4938335/3d5dafd3-5936-4f59-a57f-20a037ec2824.jpg&quot;  width=&quot;54&quot;/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;But I'm getting ahead of myself. I've broken down my field notes into three sections:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Stem cells, biotech, &amp; regulation&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;SEZs &amp; new city developments&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Panamanian urbanism, economic development, &amp; general observations&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;I. Stem cells, biotech, &amp; regulation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;We learned some conflicting information about the legal status of commercial stem cell treatments in Panamá, and I'm still trying to sort it out. If you know a doctor or lawyer who specializes in this area, &lt;a href=&quot;http://devonzuegel.com/contact&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;I'd love to hear from you&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Before the trip, I did some online sleuthing to get some background on the issue. Highlights:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Panama passed a law in 2004 making embryonic stem cell work illegal, which at the same time opened the door to legally working with adult stem cells in ways not yet approved in the US.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;div&gt;Dr. Riordan at the Panama Stem Cell Institute has performed &quot;over 10,000 procedures&quot; using stem cells to treat autism and many other conditions since they opened in Panamá in 2006. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://clippings.devonzuegel.com/post/stem-cell-therapy-for-autism-at-the-panama-stem-cell-institute&quot; rev=&quot;en_rl_none&quot;&gt;Parents' Guide to Cord Blood&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&