<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Devon Zuegel]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Devon Zuegel's personal website]]></description>
        <link>http://devonzuegel.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 19:29:32 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="http://devonzuegel.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 19:10:39 GMT</pubDate>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[404 Page Not Found]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[
<div class="jumbotron">
  <h1>404 error</h1>
  <p>The page you were looking for does not exist. :(</p>
</div>]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/404</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/404</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 04:41:25 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Home]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[
<div class="col-sm-7">
  <p>Hello! My name is Devon. I am a software engineer at <a href='http://www.affirm.com'>Affirm</a>. In my free time, I read weird blogs, work on side projects, take public transit, &amp; train for triathlons. I love reasoning about, improving, and designing systems and infrastructure.</p>
</div>
<div class="col-sm-5">
  <h4 style="margin-top:15px">Navigation</h4>
  <ul class="no-bullet paragr-line-height">
    <li><a href="#interests">   Interests</a></li>
    <li><a href="#professional">Work &amp; Professional</a></li>
    <li><a href="#media">       My favorite books, blogs, &amp; podcasts</a></li>
    <li><a href="#other">       Other things that I like</a></li>
  </ul>
</div>
<div class="col-sm-12"><a name="interests" class="anchor"></a><h2 id="interests">Interests</h2>
<p>An abridged list of things I want to learn more about and related links to interesting articles, essays, and studies on those topics. You can find a more long-form set of links <a href="../pages/links">here</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning and transporation</li>
<li>Coordination problems</li>
<li>Digital visualization tools (and generally any tools that help people think and create)<ul>
<li>Bret Victor&#39;s <a href="http://worrydream.com/#!2/LadderOfAbstraction">Ladder of Abstraction</a></li>
<li>Michael Nielsen&#39;s <a href="http://michaelnielsen.org/reinventing_explanation">call</a> to incorporate emotional impact, change habits of mind, and reduce the burden on people&#39;s short-term working memory</li>
<li>Steve Jobs&#39; description of computers as &quot;bicycles for the mind&quot; doesn&#39;t go far enough</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Ethics and Meta Ethics<ul>
<li>Deontological</li>
<li>Consequentialism, especially utilitarianism<ul>
<li>Vegetarianism and veganism</li>
<li>Effective Altruism</li>
<li>What&#39;s your utility function? Really! Let me know!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Health, nutrition, and fitness</li>
<li><a href="http://www.synbioproject.org/topics/synbio101/definition/">Synthetic biology</a><ul>
<li><a href="http://faculty.mville.edu/ParikhS/courses/chm3049/articles/Defossiling%20Fuel%20-%20How%20Synthetic%20Biology%20Can%20Transform%20Biofuel%20Production.pdf">Bio fuels</a></li>
<li>Transhumanism and the idea that humanity is a &quot;work in progress&quot;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoengineering">Geo-engineering</a></li>
<li>Linguistics<ul>
<li>The history of language</li>
<li>Natural language processing (NLP)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Psychology<ul>
<li>Rationality and biases</li>
<li>Group and organizational</li>
<li>Emergent phenomena</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Artificial intelligence<ul>
<li><a href="http://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Friendly_artificial_intelligence">Friendly AI</a> and the <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/43v/the_urgent_metaethics_of_friendly_artificial/">urgency of meta-ethics</a></li>
<li>Comparisons and parallels to human cognition</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Economics (as traditionally applied to the economy as well as all other facets of social interaction)</li>
<li>Cryptography, stenography, and information theory<ul>
<li><a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/rivest/pubs/Riv12d.slides.pdf">An abridged history</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<br/><a name="professional" class="anchor"></a><h2 id="work-professional">Work &amp; Professional</h2>
<h4 id="the-stanford-review">The Stanford Review</h4>
<p>I am Editor Emeritus of <em><a href="http://stanfordreview.org">The Stanford Review</a></em>, a bi-weekly paper that publishes investigative news and opinions articles. Some of my favorite subjects to think &amp; write about are healthcare reform, the interplay between privacy &amp; technology, tax policy, rationality, artificial intelligence, and the Second Amendment.</p>
<h4 id="section-leading">Section Leading</h4>
<p>I am a section leader for Stanford&#39;s introductory programming classes, CS 106A and 106B, in which I teach Java and C++ to students with little to no prior coding experience. As someone who came into college with no prior exposure to programming, it&#39;s particularly rewarding to see my students progress because I remember being in their position only a few years ago and know firsthand how much a little push from supportive friends can propel someone forward into the world of computer science. Teaching has also given me an even better understanding of the fundamentals of CS and an ability to communicate with people about technical problems.</p>
<br/><a name="media" class="anchor"></a><h2 id="books-blogs-podcasts-that-i-like">Books, blogs, &amp; podcasts that I like</h2>
<p>Recently I&#39;ve shifted away from just reading text (paper or otherwise), as I&#39;m always trying to optimize my time and I&#39;ve discovered that it&#39;s easy to find time to listen to podcasts and audiobooks throughout my day while I&#39;m getting dressed or walking to my classes. Currently, my favorites include:</p>
<h4 id="books">Books</h4>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Power-Broker-Robert-Moses/dp/0394720245"><em>The Power Broker</em></a> is the biography of Robert Moses, who was the NYC Parks Commissioner from the 1920s through the 1960s. Moses is more responsible for reshaping the entire face of New York City than any other individual, and his thinking influenced urban planners nationwide and beyond throughout the 20th century. Over the course of his career, Moses personally conceived and completed projects costing 27 billion dollars, more than any other US government employee ever. These projects ranged from highways and bridges to housing complexes and city parks, many of which required bulldozing entire neighborhoods and in turn displacing hundreds of thousands of NYC residents. Despite the immense impact he&#39;s had on the field of urban planning, Moses was never elected to public office. The book is not only a look into Moses&#39; fascinating life but also a unique perspective on American history and urban planning during that half century. Aside from the intensity of the story itself, the research that went into this masterpiece is just awe-inspring. The author Robert Caro is the best researcher-writer whose work I have ever read. His exhaustive series on LBJ is also fantastic; although it&#39;s more well-known and even more ridiculously in-depth than The Power Broker, I enjoyed the story about Moses a bit more because his impact was more concrete and on a more understandable scale. Also, <em>The Power Broker</em> is a story about taking a seemingly insignificant position and wielding it in a way that massively amplifies its power, whereas LBJ&#39;s story is more about climbing the ladder until you&#39;re at the top. As a side note, the narrator for the Audible recording of is fantastic.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cryptonomicon-Neal-Stephenson/dp/0060512806"><em>Cryptonomicon</em></a> by Neal Stephenson follows the intertwined exploits of a cryptanalyst working alongside Alan Turing in the 1940s, a morphine-addicted marine in the Pacific Theater of World War II, and a nerdy programmer in the 1990s who creates a safe haven for data in a world where government and corporations seek to control the flow of knowledge. Think <em>Hitchhiker&#39;s Guide to the Galaxy</em> mashed up with <em>Godel, Escher, Bach</em>, and you get <em>Cryptonomicon</em>. This book manages to be extremely fun and thought-provoking at the same time.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Season-Witch-Enchantment-Terror-Deliverance/dp/1501246917"><em>Season of the Witch</em></a> is a tapestry of San Francisco through the 60s and 70s. Growing up in the South Bay ~45 minutes away from the city, I had learned about the hippies on Haight Street and the gay-friendly culture of the Castro, but this book opened my eyes to a whole new level of richness in the city&#39;s history. I learned gems like the fact that Jim Jones and The People&#39;s Temple (of the infamous 1978 Jonestown koolaid massacre) <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/05/01/jim_jones_sinister_grip_on_san_francisco/">played an instrumental role in George Moscone&#39;s mayoral victory in 1975</a>. As a result, Moscone appointed Jones as the chairman of the SF Housing Authority Commission, and Jones gained access to California politicians like Governor Jerry Brown, SF Supervisors Dianne Feinstein and Harvey Milk, and First Lady Rosalynn Carter. In exchange for his cult&#39;s political support, these figures supported him and The People&#39;s Temple up until the day the news came in of the mass suicide at Jonestown. This shocking episode is just one of the incredible stories I learned about San Francisco&#39;s history from <em>SOTW</em>, and it completely reshaped the way I think about the city. From Jonestown and the Zebra Murders to Janis Joplin and the Grateful Dead, I can sum up what I learned in a brief sentence: SF during the span of the 60s and 70s was the real Gotham City.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.alternet.org/season-witch-dive-tumultuous-era-heroes-hippies-druggies-deadheads-and-psycho-killers">This review and interview with the author</a> offers a good sense of what the book is about.</li>
<li><blockquote>
<p>&quot;San Francisco had these demons because the rest of the country had them. But I think San Francisco dealt with them in a much more compassionate way than anywhere else in the country.&quot; – author David Talbot</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Better-Angels-Our-Nature/dp/1491518243"><em>The Better Angels of Our Nature</em></a> describes the steady decline of violence over the course of human history. I was initially skeptical of Pinker&#39;s thesis, but I can&#39;t see any way that you wouldn&#39;t be convinced of his argument after reading through the exhaustive research in this book. As a bonus, <em>The Better Angels of Our Nature</em> will leave you extremely optimistic about human progress, though at the same time you&#39;ll be horrified by how people have treated each other throughout most of human history.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Philip Pullman&#39;s <em>His Dark Materials</em> trilogy, which includes <em>The Golden Compass</em>, <em>The Subtle Knife</em>, and <em>The Amber Spyglass</em>. This was the defining book series of my childhood (wayy better than <em>Harry Potter</em>...). The books&#39; writing is so good and its themes are so enduring that I still reread them every once in a while. These books also carry the honor of being the best-quality audiobooks I&#39;ve ever listened to; rather than just one narrator reading the entire story, each character in <em>HDM</em> is read by a different actor from a famous London Shakespearian troupe, and DAMN they do a fantastic job. Some of my best childhood memories are road trips with my family, listening to the series on our way to Yosemite.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://hpmor.com"><em>Harry Potter &amp; the Methods of Rationality</em></a> takes place an alternate universe in which Harry is a child prodigy raised by scientists and &quot;enters the wizarding world armed with Enlightenment ideals and the experimental spirit&quot;. I highly suggest the <a href="http://www.hpmorpodcast.com/">HPMOR podcast</a>, which can be found on <a href="http://www.stitcher.com/">Stitcher</a>, among other places. My fitness this winter can be attributed more to this audiobook than any other single thing-- I&#39;d start off on a run or walk with my dogs and realize hours later that I&#39;d burned through 10 chapters and it was getting dark out. Long story short-- HMPOR is fantastic.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Hayek&#39;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Road-Serfdom-Documents-The-Definitive/dp/0226320553"><em>The Road to Serfdom</em></a> argues that when economic power is centralized in central planning by the government, it almost inevitably results in tyrannical dictatorship and the creation of a repressive society.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="blogs">Blogs</h4>
<p>Many of the people I&#39;m closest to I originally met because their personal websites and tweets were interesting and I figured they were probably pretty cool, too. I highly recommend it as a strategy for meeting cool people. Here are a few of the blogs that have influenced me the most:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Scott Alexander&#39;s <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com">Slate Star Codex</a> has (benevolently) forced me to reconsider my views more than any other single source of information and thought. His background as a clinical phsychiatrist (he is currently finishing up his doctor&#39;s residency) is different from that of most of the people I talk to, and that alone is very refreshing. He comes to issues ranging from feminism to the state of pharmaceutical testing with extremely original perspectives. In particular he has piqued my interest in meta-analysis of science. Not only are his ideas fantastic, but I&#39;m blown away how prolific he is. He blogs multiple times a week, bordering on every day, and yet each post consistently makes me totally reconsider the topic at hand. Scott also just seems like a genuinely good person who wants to make the world a better place with his work. My intellectual development over the past year would have been much, much slower without Slate Star Codex in my life. I hope you check it out!</p>
<ul>
<li>My friend Michael Nielsen described what&#39;s so wonderful about Scott&#39;s writing:<blockquote>
<p>Most essayists try to develop a story with a neat conclusion. But Scott develops 5 stories, all potentially the truth, all somewhat in conflict, and he tries to push them all through to the end as powerfully as possible.  So his essays aren’t about pushing a conclusion. Rather, they’re about exploring (and relating) several different ideas about where the truth may lie, to the best of his ability.  It’s a very powerful literary form.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Since we&#39;re already on the topic of Michael... <a href="http://michaelnielsen.org/">his site</a> is also wonderful! The blog spans topics like Machine Learning, digital explanations and representations, and incentive structures within academia. When I first discovered it, I spent the better part of a weekend reading it all the way through and tweeting questions, comments, and my favorite quotes at him. Highly recommend!</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://worrydream.com/">Bret Victor&#39;s site</a> is one of the most unique-in-a-good-way sites I&#39;ve seen on the web. He is a great designer of media for thought, and his work has influenced my thinking and my projects immensely. I encourage everyone to go to the site and click through some of his demos. They are very fun as well as intellectually stimulating.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Some others that I&#39;ll get around to writing descriptions of one day:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://marginalrevolution.com">Marginal Revolution</a></li>
<li><a href="http://sf.streetsblog.org">Streetsblog SF</a></li>
<li><a href="http://me.vekun.com">Fuzzy Notepad</a></li>
</ul>
<h4 id="podcasts">Podcasts</h4>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://freakonomics.com/radio/freakonomics-radio-podcast-archive/"><em>Freakonomics Radio</em></a> is a weekly podcast that discusses &quot;the hidden side of everything&quot;. My favorite episodes include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://freakonomics.com/2014/12/11/the-troubled-cremation-of-stevie-the-cat-a-freakonomics-radio-rebroadcast/">&quot;The Troubled Cremation of Stevie the Cat&quot;</a></li>
<li><a href="http://freakonomics.com/2014/11/13/why-do-people-keep-having-children-a-new-freakonomics-radio-podcast/">&quot;Why Do People Keep Having Children?&quot;</a></li>
<li><a href="http://freakonomics.com/2014/10/09/how-to-raise-money-without-killing-a-kitten-a-freakonomics-radio-rebroadcast/">&quot;How to Raise Money Without Killing a Kitten&quot;</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://99pi.org"><em>99% Invisible</em></a> is about design, architecture, and urban planning. In a parallel universe I would have loved to be an architect, so this podcast is my weekly dose of how buildings and spaces affect the history around them. 99pi makes me consider aspects of cities I don’t normally think about, and it&#39;s particularly fun to listen to while walking through the SoMa district in San Francico on my way to work each morning. The episodes are nicely bite-sized too, about 25 minutes each. While the content of the show is great, the most unique part is that the podcast is just beautifully done – it is really a piece of audio art, with so much more depth and richness than traditional radio, and Roman Mars&#39; (the host) voice is like velvet.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://npr.org/sections/money"><em>Planet Money</em></a> deep-dives into some aspect of the economy twice a week. In one episode, they documented the process of creating an off-shore company, and in another they put $1,000 into shorting the US stock market. Tragically, I finally finished the hundreds of episodes recorded since Planet Money debuted in 2008, so now I have to actually wait a few days between each episode!</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://youarenotsosmart.com/"><em>You Are Not So Smart</em></a> explores self delusion, common logical fallacies, and the influence of cognitive biases on our thinking.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://backstoryradio.org/how-to-listen/podcast-2/"><em>Backstory</em></a> is hosted by three U.S. historians whose areas of expertise are the 1700s, 1800s, and 1900s respectively. Each episode takes a single theme (e.g. &quot;Body Politics: Disability in America&quot;, &quot;Banned: A History of Censorship&quot;, &quot;Fear Tactics: A History of Domestic Terrorism&quot;), and over the course of an hour they use that theme as a lens to look through a range of time periods in American history. The show is very high quality, and I&#39;ve learned a lot of things about US history that I likely never would have learned otherwise.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://thisiscriminal.com/"><em>Criminal</em></a> tells &quot;stories of people who&#39;ve done wrong, been wronged, or gotten caught somewhere in the middle&quot;.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>And a few others (in no particular order) for which I&#39;ll (maybe) get around to writing descriptions later:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://TODO"><em>The Psychology of Attractiveness</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://gastropod.com"><em>Gastropod</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://thehistoryofsingapore.com/"><em>The History of Singapore</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.wnyc.org/shows/tnyradiohour"><em>The New Yorker Radio Hour</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://psychologyofattractivenesspodcast.blogspot.com/"><em>The Bike Shed</em></a> – Thoughtbot&#39;s podcast about programming and web design, particularly in Ruby</li>
<li><a href="http://tentative.fm/"><em>Tentative</em></a> – Thoughtbot&#39;s podcast about digital product design</li>
<li><a href="https://imaginaryworldspodcast.org"><em>Imaginary Worlds</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/open-account-with-suchin-pak/id1037408626?mt=2"><em>Open Account</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://econtalk.org"><em>EconTalk</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://radiolab.org/series/podcasts"><em>Radiolab</em></a></li>
<li><a href="www.npr.org/podcasts/510308/hidden-brain"><em>Hidden Brain</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.thisamericanlife.org/podcast"><em>This American Life</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://radioopensource.org/"><em>Open Source with Christopher Lydon</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://15minutehistory.org"><em>15 Minute History</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://thememorypalace.us"><em>The Memory Palace</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.dancarlin.com/hardcore-history-series"><em>Dan Carlin&#39;s Hardcore History</em></a></li>
<li><a href="http://rationallyspeakingpodcast.org"><em>Rationally Speaking</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://radio.economist.com"><em>The Economist Radio</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://gimletmedia.com/show/startup/"><em>StartUp Podcast</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://gimletmedia.com/show/reply-all/"><em>Reply All</em></a></li>
</ul>
<br/><a name="other" class="anchor"></a><h2 id="other-things-that-i-like">Other things that I like</h2>
<ul>
<li>An <strong>aptronym</strong> is a name aptly suited to its owner. A few of my favorite <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aptronym#Notable_examples">notable examples</a>:<ul>
<li>Sara Blizzard, meteorologist</li>
<li>John Carbon, American organic chemist</li>
<li>Bernie Madoff, who <em>made off</em> with a lot of other people&#39;s money</li>
<li>Marina Stepanova, former Soviet hurdler, first woman to run under 53 seconds in the 400 m hurdles</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Triathlons, especially coastal ones</li>
<li><a href="./posts/workflow-optimizations-customizations">Workflow optimization</a>–– I probably spend more time optimizing my workflow than I actually save.</li>
</ul>

</div>]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 19:15:08 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Contact]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[
<div class="contact col-sm-4">
  <h4>Github</h4><a href="http://github.com/devonzuegel">github.com/devonzuegel</a>
  <h4>Twitter</h4><a href="http://twitter.com/devonzuegel">@devonzuegel</a>
  <h4>Email</h4><a href="mailto:devonz@cs.stanford.edu">devonz@cs.stanford.edu</a>
  <h4>Instapaper</h4><a href="https://www.instapaper.com/p/devonzuegel">devonzuegel</a>
  <h4></h4><a></a>
  <h4>Resume</h4><a href="/assets/Devon_Zuegel--Resume.pdf">PDF</a>
</div>
<div class="col-sm-8"><p>This site is where I can riff on ideas, be wrong, and learn from those mistakes. Of course I try to be correct, and I always write what I believe to be true, but the greatest value most often comes from someone messaging me to point out a body of research I missed or angle I misinterpreted.</p>
<p>In this vein, please don&#39;t hesitate to let me know what you think! The whole point is to share what I know and to learn the rest.</p>

</div>
<div class="col-xs-12">
  <h4>Spotify</h4>
  <div class="space triple"></div>
  <iframe src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify%3Auser%3A123589098%3Aplaylist%3A4qo0rRTKF8bFogGPWc7eJ3&amp;theme=white" width="300" height="380" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true"></iframe>
  <div class="space triple"></div>
</div>]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/pages/contact</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/pages/contact</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 20:00:18 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Writing]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/podcast-and-audiobook-starter-kit"><img src="http://cdn8.openculture.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/bigstock_Audio_book_14340599-e1330386218724.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/podcast-and-audiobook-starter-kit">Podcast &amp; Audiobook Starter Kit</a></h3>
    <div class="time">26 August 2016</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/ode-to-audio"><img src="http://www.podcastdojo.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/HeadphoneMic-300x300.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/ode-to-audio">Ode to Audio: Why You Should Give Podcasts and Audiobooks a Chance</a></h3>
    <div class="time">25 August 2016</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/walkable-cities"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/gfx2zyn.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/walkable-cities">We Should Be Building Cities For People, Not Cars</a></h3>
    <div class="time">15 August 2016</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/google-maps-convinced-me-to-ditch-my-car"><img src="http://www.geospatialworld.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/Google.jpeg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/google-maps-convinced-me-to-ditch-my-car">Google Maps Convinced Me to Ditch My Car</a></h3>
    <div class="time">30 June 2016</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/death-and-life-of-company-towns"><img src="http://uudb.org/images/georgepullman4.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/death-and-life-of-company-towns">The Death and Life of American Company Towns</a></h3>
    <div class="time">29 June 2016</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/company-towns"><img src="http://ffden-2.phys.uaf.edu/webproj/212_spring_2014/Jessica_Garvin/jessica_garvin/Images/carousel.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/company-towns">A Square Deal: The Legacy of Company Towns</a></h3>
    <div class="time">24 June 2016</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/visual-technology"><img src="../assets/headline-images/horsehead-nebula.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/visual-technology">Visual Technology</a></h3>
    <div class="time">24 February 2016</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/last-mile-problem"><img src="../assets/headline-images/last-mile.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/last-mile-problem">The Last Mile Problem</a></h3>
    <div class="time">02 December 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/my-sublime-setup"><img src="../assets/headline-images/sublime-text_teaser.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/my-sublime-setup">My Text Editor is Absolutely Sublime</a></h3>
    <div class="time">27 November 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/a-bus-named-desire"><img src="../assets/headline-images/public-bus-named-desire.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/a-bus-named-desire">A Public Bus Named Desire</a></h3>
    <div class="time">26 November 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/suburbs-a-deceptive-utopia"><img src="../assets/headline-images/suburbs.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/suburbs-a-deceptive-utopia">The Death and Life of (not-so-)Great American Suburbs</a></h3>
    <div class="time">02 November 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/streetcars-vs-buses-primer"><img src="../assets/headline-images/Berlin-Rapid-Transit-Map.gif"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/streetcars-vs-buses-primer">A Primer on the Streetcars vs Buses debate</a></h3>
    <div class="time">21 October 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/workflow-optimizations-customizations"><img src="../assets/headline-images/workflow-optimizations-customizations.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/workflow-optimizations-customizations">Workflow optimizations &amp; customizations</a></h3>
    <div class="time">23 September 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/pomodoro-technique"><img src="../assets/headline-images/pomodoro.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/pomodoro-technique">Pomodoro</a></h3>
    <div class="time">03 August 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/cities-the-ultimate-sharing-economy"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rH3W1T7.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/cities-the-ultimate-sharing-economy">Cities: The Ultimate Sharing Economy</a></h3>
    <div class="time">24 May 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/automator-workflow-to-stitch-pdfs-together-into-a-single-document"><img src="../assets/headline-images/Automator_icon.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/automator-workflow-to-stitch-pdfs-together-into-a-single-document">Automator Workflow to stitch PDFs into a single document</a></h3>
    <div class="time">19 March 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/zsh-aliases"><img src="../assets/headline-images/zsh-shell.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/zsh-aliases">My zsh aliases</a></h3>
    <div class="time">17 March 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/why-i-am-no-longer-a-libertarian"><img src="../assets/headline-images/no-longer-libertarian.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/why-i-am-no-longer-a-libertarian">Why I am no longer a Libertarian</a></h3>
    <div class="time">14 February 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/batch-installing-fonts-in-multiple-subfolders"><img src="../assets/headline-images/batch-installing-fonts.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/batch-installing-fonts-in-multiple-subfolders">Batch installing fonts in multiple subdirectories</a></h3>
    <div class="time">01 February 2015</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/economic-conservatives-should-champion-female-technologists"><img src="../assets/headline-images/female-tech.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/economic-conservatives-should-champion-female-technologists">Economic Conservatives Should Champion Female Technologists</a></h3>
    <div class="time">17 October 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/dont-rush-to-embrace-mandatory-expulsion"><img src="../assets/headline-images/mandatory-expulsion.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/dont-rush-to-embrace-mandatory-expulsion">Don’t Rush to Embrace Mandatory Expulsion Until All Rights Protected</a></h3>
    <div class="time">04 June 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/the-new-campus-radicals"><img src="../assets/headline-images/new-campus-radicals.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/the-new-campus-radicals">Editor's Note: The New Campus Radicals</a></h3>
    <div class="time">01 June 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/responding-rationally-to-a-tragedy"><img src="//www.trbimg.com/img-53814c23/turbine/la-me-ln-isla-vista-shooting-suspect-vowed-war-on-women-sorority-20140524"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/responding-rationally-to-a-tragedy">Responding Rationally to a Tragedy</a></h3>
    <div class="time">26 May 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/prohibition-anarchy-how-the-war-on-drugs-helps-violence-flourish"><img src="//stanfordreview.org/wp-content/uploads/Mexico-articleLarge.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/prohibition-anarchy-how-the-war-on-drugs-helps-violence-flourish">Prohibition &amp; Anarchy: How the War on Drugs helps Violence Flourish</a></h3>
    <div class="time">22 May 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/what-happened-at-mtgox-the-collapse-of-the-worlds-largest-bitcoin-exchange"><img src="//stanfordreview.org/wp-content/uploads/mtgox_where_is_our_money-1024x682.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/what-happened-at-mtgox-the-collapse-of-the-worlds-largest-bitcoin-exchange">What happened at MtGox? The Collapse of the World's Largest Bitcoin Exchange</a></h3>
    <div class="time">22 April 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/consistency-is-key-a-letter-to-the-stanford-gsc"><img src="//lh4.googleusercontent.com/hRaaxxtSKdKqWXwZ2uF88RvKJElTK21Yr8NzbMAoQ6Fz77936SC28eDZMGZKH9Fv1hm7vhJqTzR3XiXf7U6XnrTfd1KZiCOmto3JA72OexeLXKFcwCg6ughP4PpGZSH6qA"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/consistency-is-key-a-letter-to-the-stanford-gsc">Consistency is Key: A Letter to the Stanford GSC</a></h3>
    <div class="time">19 April 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/beginning-of-volume-letter"><img src="//stanfordreview.org/wp-content/uploads/political_square.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/beginning-of-volume-letter">Beginning of Volume Letter</a></h3>
    <div class="time">23 February 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/mortgaging-the-millennials-future"><img src="//lh3.googleusercontent.com/ILy2T6hLMXc90tFuQr7MWRUj9mKoGB6f-dANvsXRRwgmTsR7wmdK7U1D3DDuGuyNpwZTxhlgbJxp_pYTGIgWGOA3jj0o4i_U0bADZiWJtR0WSEYhL_RM7XVE0Q"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/mortgaging-the-millennials-future">Mortgaging the Millennials’ Future</a></h3>
    <div class="time">23 January 2014</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/the-affordable-care-act-you"><img src="//stanfordreview.org/wp-content/uploads/obamacare_survey_pie_chart.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/the-affordable-care-act-you">The Affordable Care Act &amp; You</a></h3>
    <div class="time">08 December 2013</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/an-interview-with-dr-bhattacharya"><img src="//iis-db.stanford.edu/news/3405/3405-small_jay_square..jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/an-interview-with-dr-bhattacharya">An Interview with Dr. Bhattacharya</a></h3>
    <div class="time">05 December 2013</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/is-the-u-s-tax-code-fair"><img src="//stanfordreview.org/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2013-02-19-at-11.19.11-AM-300x164.png"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/is-the-u-s-tax-code-fair">Is the U.S. Tax Code Fair?</a></h3>
    <div class="time">17 February 2013</div>
  </div>
</div>
<div class="headline">
  <div class="circle small pull-left"><a href="/posts/why-college-campuses-should-allow-concealed-carry"><img src="//stanfordreview.org/wp-content/uploads/Shooting_range_Glockwikimediacommons-300x225.jpg"/></a></div>
  <div class="title pull-left">
    <h3><a href="/posts/why-college-campuses-should-allow-concealed-carry">Why College Campuses Should Allow Concealed Carry</a></h3>
    <div class="time">18 January 2013</div>
  </div>
</div>]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/pages/posts</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/pages/posts</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 08:06:04 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Links]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<!-- collection: pages -->
<p>This is where I collect some of the ideas, historical facts, anecdotes, etc. that I would like more people to know about or just plain don&#39;t want to forget. I update it sporadically, and the process is not systematic in any way.</p>
<h2 id="cybernetics-artificial-intelligence">Cybernetics &amp; Artificial Intelligence</h2>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cybernetics"><strong>Cybernetics</strong></a> is the study of the structures, constraints, and possiblities of regulatory systems. It abstracts concepts such as learning, adaptation, emergence, and communication from their mechanical / physical / biological / cognitive / social contexts and studies the influence of feedback loops and circular causal relationships.</p>
<h4 id="artificial-genocide">Artificial Genocide</h4>
<p><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2002/04/seeing-around-corners/302471/">Atlantic article</a></p>
<p><img src="http://cdn.theatlantic.com/static/coma/images/issues/200204/figure5-vs.gif" alt=""></p>
<blockquote>
<p>If societies can order themselves systematically but unconsciously, it stands to reason that they can also disorder themselves systematically but unconsciously</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 id="project-cybersyn-div-class-time-pull-right-style-margin-2px-15-feb-2015-div-">Project Cybersyn <div class='time pull-right' style='margin:2px'>15 Feb 2015</div></h4>
<p><img src='http://www.redpepper.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/cybersyn.jpg' style='float:right; margin:15px; max-width:60%'/></p>
<p>Chile&#39;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Cybersyn"><strong>Project Cybersyn</strong></a> was a decision support system that aided in the management of the national economy based on a neural network approach to organizational design. Among other tasks, Cybersyn monitored production indicators directly in factories through 500 telex machines. This served to (1) alert workers and in extreme cases the central government if production indicators fell outise of acceptable ranges and (2) provide inputs into an economic simulation that the government could use to forecast the outcome of various decisions.</p>
<p>This system played a key role in the newly nationalized sectors of Chile&#39;s economy from 1971-1973, but the project was destroyed following the military coup in September 1973.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>The futuristic operations room was furnished with seven swivel chairs (considered the best for creativity).</em></p>
</blockquote>
<!-- ## Rationality & Cognitive Biases -->
<h2 id="political-philosophy">Political Philosophy</h2>
<h4 id="politics-is-the-mindkiller-div-class-time-pull-right-style-margin-2px-14-feb-2015-div-">Politics is the Mindkiller <div class='time pull-right' style='margin:2px'>14 Feb 2015</div></h4>
<p>I encourage everyone with the slightest political conviction and particularly those interested in pursuing a career in politics to read <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/gw/politics_is_the_mindkiller/"><strong>Politics is the Mindkiller</strong></a>. The essay&#39;s core argument is that &quot;It&#39;s just better for the spiritual growth of a community to discuss an issue without invoking color politics.&quot; Reading this piece marked a turning point in my intellectual development as someone with a history of strongly identifying with a particular political tribe (Libertarianism).</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Politics is an extension of war.  Arguments are soldiers.  Once you know which side you&#39;re on, you must support all arguments of that side, and attack all arguments that appear to favor the enemy side; otherwise it&#39;s like stabbing your soldiers in the back—providing aid and comfort to the enemy.  People who would be level-headed about evenhandedly weighing all sides of an issue in their professional life as scientists, can suddenly turn into slogan-chanting zombies when there&#39;s a Blue or Green position on an issue...</em></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-studies">Miscellaneous studies</h2>
<h4 id="addiction-at-rat-park-div-class-time-pull-right-style-margin-2px-15-feb-2015-div-">Addiction at Rat Park <div class='time pull-right' style='margin:2px'>15 Feb 2015</div></h4>
<p><img src='http://sos.fishki.net/upload/en/201309/18/13402/d501eedb0fa9212d323b6b6d7681fa7f.png' style='float:right; margin:15px; max-width:50%'></p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rat_Park?utm_source=hackernewsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=learn"><strong>Rat Park</strong></a> was 1970s study suggesting that addiction to opiates can be attributed to isolation and severe distress rather than any addictive property of the drug istelf. Principal investigator Bruce Alexander argued that prior addiction-related experiments are misrepresentative of the phenomenon because the rats were kept in cramped metal cages, tethered to a self-injection apparatus.</p>
<p>Alexander built a &quot;Rat Park&quot; 200 times the area of a standard laboratory cage with an abundance of food and toys, and he populated the colony with ~20 rats. The rats had previously been forced to consume opiates for over two months. One group of these rats was brought to the park, while a control group was isolated in typical small cages. Both cohorts were given a choice between plain water and water laced with morphine. Those in Rat Park rarely chose the drugged water; meanwhile, the control group consumed much more morphine. Alexandar concluded that the rats wished to not disrupt their normal social behavior, and that while there were &quot;some minor withdrawl signs&quot; such as twitching, &quot;there were none of the mythic seizures and sweats you so often hear about&quot; among the rats in Rat Park.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Although the use of opiates in the United States and England during the 19th century was greater than it is now, the incidence of dependence and addiction never reached one percent of the population and was declining at the end of the century. In Britain, heroin has been widely used in medication for coughs, diarrhea, and chronic pain until the present day; <strong>in 1972, British doctors prescribed 29 millions of doses of heroin to patients, yet a 1982 study of the statistics on iatrogenic addiction in the UK showed a &quot;virtual absence&quot; of such addicts</strong>. Recent research confirms that many people use heroin regularly for years, for either recreational or medical purposes, without becoming addicted.</em></p>
</blockquote>
]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/pages/links</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/pages/links</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 02:20:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Projects]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript"> // Hack to fix scrolling to Mr Schelling's Neighborhood 
  document.body.scrollTop = document.documentElement.scrollTop = 0;
</script>

<h1 id="projects">Projects</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mfp-api">MyFitnessPal API</a></li>
<li><a href="#isostamp">Isostamp</a></li>
<li><a href="#schelling-neighborhood">Mr. Schelling&#39;s Neighborhood</a></li>
<li><a href="#tiddly-lisp">TiddlyLisp</a></li>
<li><a href="#instanote">Instanote</a></li>
<li><a href="#congressional-bills">Congressional Bill Outcome Predictor</a></li>
<li><a href="#affitto">Affitto</a></li>
<li><a href="#my-evernote">My Evernote</a></li>
<li><a href="#zen-writer">Zen Writer</a></li>
<li><a href="#origami-js">OrigamiJS</a></li>
<li><a href="#fiesta">Fiesta: Machine Translator</a></li>
<li><a href="#octagon">Octagon</a></li>
<li><a href="#paper-trail">Paper Trail</a></li>
<li><a href="#in-other-words">In Other Words</a></li>
</ul>
<div class='space triple'></div><div class='space'></div>

<p><a name='mfp-api' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="myfitnesspal-api">MyFitnessPal API</h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>August - September 2016</div><br></div>

<p>I&#39;ve tracked my eating habits for the past eight years, and I&#39;ve since added other health and productivity metrics. Data have piled up in the spreadsheets, services, and other tools I&#39;ve used to collect these measurements. So far I&#39;ve done little with it, but I always imagined that they would one day uncover some pattern that would suggest changes in the way I eat, work, or exercise.</p>
<p>So in 2016 when I started experiencing extreme fatigue nearly every afternoon, I decided to investigate whether there was a connection between the food I was eating and my energy levels. My hypothesis was that eating carbohydrates was making me “crash” in the afternoon, because I tended to feel better those days I stuck with just veggies and protein for lunch.</p>
<p>To test this hypothesis, I went to MyFitnessPal (MFP), where I&#39;d been collecting data about my eating habits since high school. To my dismay, they did not have a public API or even a tool that would let me export more than a few months of data at a time. I found a few third-party tools that let me cobble together the logs, but they felt as if they were duct-taped together.</p>
<p>At this point, any reasonable person would have just accepted this fact and used the manual workarounds to export the data. After all, my goal was to find data to confirm or falsify my hypothesis, not to have a beautiful REST API from which I could continuously pull my food logs.</p>
<p>Instead of being reasonable person, I decided to build a little service that would pull all of my logs each day, persist it to a separate database, and then surface the data with a JSON API. I initially planned to write a simple web scraper to do the retrieval work. With a bit more digging through Github&#39;s less-than-spectacular search (and encouragement from John &lt;3), I found a project by someone even less reasonable than me that inspired the approach I ended up taking.</p>
<p>Nathan Reynolds (<a href="https://github.com/nathforge">nathforge</a> on Github) had figured out that in fact MyFitnessPal <em>did</em> have an API, it just was for internal use in the official iPhone app only. Not only was the API completely undocumented, but the MFP team had created a custom byte encoding by which to send the data. I still have no idea how he figured out the spec of this encoding, because a lot of the design choices made appear completely random. However he did it, Nathan had built up this codec that took the stream of bytes and parsed them into a human-readable form.</p>
<p>Nathan&#39;s <a href="https://github.com/nathforge/myfitnesspal-sync"><code>myfitnesspal-sync</code></a> was a goldmine for understanding MFP&#39;s arcane encoding, but it had some drawbacks. The package didn&#39;t support every type of packet, which mean I would have had to extend his code to be able to sync all of my data from MFP. Also, I didn&#39;t particularly like the interface he&#39;d designed, and it was completely untested. It also had to be manually run from the command line, whereas I wanted something that would continuously sync the data. On top of all this, I&#39;d be looking for a reason to write some Ruby this summer, so I figured this was a good excuse to do that.</p>
<p>I first wrote a package to decode the MFP packets and the encode human-readable data back into the byte form. All the while I was plagiarizing Nathan&#39;s detective work (yay open source!). Thanks Nathan, you are a hero.</p>
<p>Once I was satisfied with my Ruby implementation of the codec, I built a tiny Sinatra API to surface the data. This part is still a work-in-progress. It <em>works</em>, but it isn&#39;t particularly robust. There&#39;s still a bit more work to do.</p>
<p>I still haven&#39;t gotten around to a significant amount of data analysis. I did use Metabase to analyze the data in my Heroku Postgres instance over the holidays, but there&#39;s definitely more to dig into.</p>
<p>You can find the code for the full API <a href="https://github.com/devonzuegel/myfitnesspal-ruby">on Github</a>. The module for just the codec implementation is in that repository in the <a href="https://github.com/devonzuegel/myfitnesspal-ruby/tree/master/lib"><code>lib</code></a> directory. Once the API itself is stable, I&#39;ll make it available to anyone who wants to sync and retrieve their MFP data.</p>
<p><a name='isostamp' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-isostamp-https-isostamp-org-"><a href="https://isostamp.org">Isostamp</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>March - July 2016</div><br></div>

<p><a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/cb100338x">Isotopic signature transfer and mass pattern prediction (Isostamp)</a> is an enabling technique for chemically-directed proteomics. Specifically, it is an algorithm for the targeted detection and identification of modified species by mass spectrometry (MS).</p>
<p>Will Byrd and I worked with the Bertozzi Lab to develop their Isostamp algorithm. We also built a simple API so developers can run the executable in the cloud, and we built a web application that enables other labs to use Isostamp to upload and analyze their own data.</p>
<p>You can find the code for the API at <a href="https://github.com/devonzuegel/tagfinder-api">github.com/devonzuegel/tagfinder-api</a>.</p>
<p>You can upload your own data and learn more about Isostamp at <a href="Isostamp.org">Isostamp.org</a>, and you can find the code for the web app at <a href="https://github.com/devonzuegel/Isostamp-web-v2">github.com/devonzuegel/Isostamp-web-v2</a>.</p>
<p>We will be open-sourcing the C++ code for the algorithm soon.</p>
<p><a name='schelling-neighborhood' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-mr-schelling-s-neighborhood-https-rawgit-com-devonzuegel-affitto-master-models-mr-schellings-neighborhood-mr-schellings-neighborhood-html-"><a href="https://rawgit.com/devonzuegel/affitto/master/models/mr-schellings-neighborhood/mr-schellings-neighborhood.html">Mr. Schelling&#39;s Neighborhood</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>July 2016</div><br></div>

<p>Ever since reading about Schelling&#39;s <a href="http://isites.harvard.edu/fs/docs/icb.topic185351.files/shelling1.pdf">&quot;general theory of tipping&quot;</a> in <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2002/04/seeing-around-corners/302471/"><em>Seeing Around Corners</em></a>, I&#39;ve wanted to replicate some of his models and play around with agent-based modeling as a technique.</p>
<p>Schelling&#39;s model of segregation found that if individuals have even just a slight preference to be surrounded by people of their own group or race, the emergent effect across a population can be total segregation, even if that is not the intention of any specific agent. This effect can be seen with a simple ABM, which I&#39;ve implemented below.</p>
<p>You are looking at a birds-eye view of a simulated neighborhood containing two groups, blue and red with a handful of blank spaces. To start, the blues and reds are randomly distributed. Then, frame after frame, the agents are allowed to move. The agent is happy with its position if its nearest neighbors include at least a certain number of its own color; otherwise, they move to a random open space on the map.</p>
<p>The default number of same-colored neighbors required to make an agent satisfied with its location is the threshold, and the percent of &quot;empty lost&quot; on the map is the percent open. You can adjust these with the controls in the top right corner of the model.</p>
<iframe src='https://rawgit.com/devonzuegel/affitto/master/models/mr-schellings-neighborhood/mr-schellings-neighborhood-small.html' style='width:100%; height: 270px;' frameborder='no' border='0'></iframe>

<p>You can find the ABM code on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/affitto/master/models/mr-schellings-neighborhood/mr-schellings-neighborhood.coffee">Github</a>, and you can see a larger version of the model <a href="https://rawgit.com/devonzuegel/affitto/master/models/mr-schellings-neighborhood/mr-schellings-neighborhood.html">here</a>.</p>
<p><a name='tiddly-lisp' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-tiddlylisp-github-com-devonzuegel-tiddly-lisp-"><a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/tiddly-lisp">TiddlyLisp</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>January 2016</div><br></div>

<p>To learn the fundamentals of Lisp, I built a little interpreter based on Michael Nielsen&#39;s fantastic blog post <a href="http://www.michaelnielsen.org/ddi/lisp-as-the-maxwells-equations-of-software/"><em>Lisp as the Maxwell&#39;s Equations of Software</em></a>. I included extensions to resolve some of the challenge problems he mentioned at the end of the post, too.</p>
<p>You can find the code for the interpreter on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/tiddly-lisp">Github</a>.</p>
<p><a name='instanote' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-instanote-https-instanote-archive-herokuapp-com-"><a href="https://instanote-archive.herokuapp.com">Instanote</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>January 2016</div><br></div>

<p>About a month ago, I started using Instapaper obsessively. However, it left me with one major problem – all of my Instapaper bookmarks and highlights were isolated from the knowledge that I (obsessively) store in Evernote, and I wanted to have them all in one place. After all, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_base">personal knowledge base</a> is useless if it doesn&#39;t contain half of the things I read throughout the day.</p>
<p>Instanote solves this problem by syncing the text of my archived Instapaper bookmarks with their respective highlights into Evernote every 10 minutes. I figured other people might have the same frustration with Instapaper, so I built out a little Heroku app that allows other people to sign up too rather than just hard-coding my login info into a hacky script.</p>
<p>You can sign up at <a href="https://instanote-archive.herokuapp.com">instanote-archive.herokuapp.com</a> and see the source code on <a href="https://github.com/devonzuegel/instanote-archive">Github</a>.</p>
<p><a name='congressional-bills' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-congressional-bill-outcome-predictor-http-devonzuegel-com-bills-"><a href="http://devonzuegel.com/bills/">Congressional Bill Outcome Predictor</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>December 2015</div><br></div>

<p>Emma Marriott, Arushi Jain, and I built a predictor that identifies which US bills will succeed in the House &amp; Senate. We tried several different prediction methods, including: Naive Bayes with and without Principal Component Analysis (PCA), Logistic Regression, Support Vector Machine (SVM) with PCA, and Perceptron with PCA. PCA identified the <code>500</code> most important features of a set of <code>11,000</code>. Each predictor was modeled on data from the 109th – 113th Congresses from a wide range of structured &amp; unstructured sources, including lobbying information. SVM with PCA proved to be the best model. It predicted bill outcomes with <code>94%</code> precision &amp; <code>87%</code> recall, resulting in an F-measure of <code>0.92</code>.</p>
<p>You can learn more about our research and data <a href="http://devonzuegel.com/bills/">here</a>.</p>
<p><a name='affitto' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-affitto-github-com-devonzuegel-affitto-"><a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/affitto">Affitto</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>November 2015</div><br></div>

<p>San Francisco and the greater Bay Area have been struggling with housing shortages and decisions about how to best serve the community with policies to deal with this situation. At a micro level, we have a fairly good understanding of how individuals make economic decisions such as where tenants choose to live and how much rent landlords choose to charge. However, we lack tools to model the complex interactions of millions of individuals simultaneously making decisions and the emergent phenomena that result from these interactions.</p>
<p>John Luttig and I built an Agent Based Model (ABM) to simulate emergent behavior within housing markets and explore the impact of policies such as rent control and zoning regulations. With this project, we aim to provide a tool for policymakers and stakeholders to better understand these interactions that in aggregate comprise the housing market. Understanding large-scale systems requires understanding how the results of individual actions can be more than the sum of its parts. We used ABM to simulate the actions and interactions of tenants and landlords.</p>
<p>Here is a small version of one of our models. You may have to close the controls (by clicking the bottom of the control panel) in order to see the full simulation.</p>
<iframe src='http://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://raw.githubusercontent.com/devonzuegel/affitto/blob/master/models/model2-small/model.html' style='width:100%; height: 390px;' frameborder='no' border='0'></iframe>

<p>You can find the ABM code, housing data with which we initialized the model, and further information on the analysis we performed on the resulting network at <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/affitto">github.com/devonzuegel/affitto</a>. You can see a larger version of the model <a href="http://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://raw.githubusercontent.com/devonzuegel/affitto/blob/master/models/model2/model.html">here</a>.</p>
<p><a name='my-evernote' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-my-evernote-myevernote-co-"><a href="//myevernote.co">My Evernote</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>July 2015</div><br></div>

<p>I love Evernote. On any given day I usually create about 15 notes, ranging from highlighted blog posts and articles to trip itineraries and to-do lists. The bulk of these notes are clippings from around the web that I&#39;ve read and annotated with Evernote&#39;s <a href="//evernote.com/clearly/">Clearly extension</a>.</p>
<p>Evernote has lots of great sharing capabilities, including joint notebooks, public links, and social sharing. However, I&#39;ve always wanted to publish a sort of feed that shares a select set from my annotated notes and displays what my friends have read. What I want is a bit like Medium, but where the posts aren&#39;t necessarily from that platform, simply clipped with Evernote into a notebook.</p>
<p>As a fun way to solve this little problem of mine and to teach myself more about Rails testing frameworks, I&#39;m working on a little app called <a href="//myevernote.co">My Evernote</a>. When I&#39;m done, it&#39;ll automatically sync all of your notes except those you especially tag <code>#private</code>. Then each evening you receive an email asking which of the synced notes you want to &quot;publish&quot; on your feed. It&#39;s a simple app, but I quickly learned that the Evernote documentation for Rails is basically non-existent, so it&#39;s also been a fun way to add to that.</p>
<p><img src="../assets/my-evernote.png" alt=""></p>
<p>You can find the open source code for the project on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/my-evernote">Github</a> and the app at <a href="//myevernote.co">myevernote.co</a>.</p>
<p><a name='zen-writer' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-zen-writer-zenwriter-io-"><a href="//zenwriter.io">Zen Writer</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>June 2015</div><br></div>

<p>The most difficult part of writing is that first draft. Putting your ideas to paper to generate that initial content is hard, because it&#39;s natural to edit your thoughts while translating them into words. However, this can severely hamper progress and creativity during early drafts. I&#39;ve learned that I write better content faster if I don&#39;t censor myself initially and then only allow myself to revise and edit after I&#39;ve exhausted my ideas. However, it&#39;s extremely difficult to contain that urge to filter out the less well-formed ideas.</p>
<p>During spring quarter finals, I was assigned a 10 page paper. Just three days before it was due I had a one page draft despite hours of research and staring at a blank screen. I had lots of ideas in my head, but every time I started typing I ended up using the delete button almost as much as all my other keys combined.</p>
<p>Since I wasn&#39;t making any progress anyways, I decided to take a break and built a tiny text editor called <a href="//zenwriter.io">Zen Writer</a>. It disables the delete button, highlights the current line, and fades out past content so that your attention is focused on moving forward and generating more content.</p>
<p>It didn&#39;t take much work to build a rough version, and as soon as I finished I was back to writing that first draft of my paper. In the first 15 minutes, I generated about 600 words. When I went back to revise what I&#39;d written, I was surprised to find that most of my changes were to fix minor typos rather than large, conceptual revisions.</p>
<p>I finished that first draft in just over 2 hours and spent another hour the following day to revise my work, and the resulting paper was among the best I&#39;ve written in my time at Stanford. Since then, I use Zen Writer every time I get stuck writing, from emails to blog posts to READMEs. I hope other people find it useful too, though I will warn you that it&#39;s still very rough and simple!</p>
<p>You can find the open source code for the project on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/zen-writer">Github</a> and the app at <a href="//zenwriter.io">zenwriter.io</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. As a more robust solution to this problem, I now use the <a href="http://www.96problems.com/rough-draft/">First Draft</a> Mac app from <a href="http://www.96problems.com/">96 Problems</a>. It offers all the features I built, planned to build, or never even realized I needed in ZenWriter. Ben and the whole team are super responsive and helpful too, so in short I highly recommend the app if you&#39;re looking for a tool to solve this problem!</p>
<p><a name='origami-js' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-origamijs-htmlpreview-github-io-https-raw-githubusercontent-com-devonzuegel-origamijs-master-example-coffee-html-"><a href="//htmlpreview.github.io/?https://raw.githubusercontent.com/devonzuegel/origamijs/master/example-coffee.html">OrigamiJS</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>March 2015</div><br></div>

<p>Over spring break I decided I wanted to play around with coffeescript, so I built a little script to hierarchically fold elements on a webpage. I originally built it so I could fold long blog posts and class notes I had written in Markdown. The idea was inspired by the great header folding in <a href="http://marked2app.com/">Marked2</a>, my favorite Markdown previewer, so by default Origamijs folds traditional <code>&lt;h*&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> elements as defined by Markdown. Origamijs also allows clients to define their own hierarchy, in the case that they&#39;re using unique tags or prefer to ignore certain levels of the traditional Markdown tag hierarchy.</p>
<p>You can find the open source code for the project on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/origamijs">Github</a> and example usage <a href="//htmlpreview.github.io/?https://raw.githubusercontent.com/devonzuegel/origamijs/master/example-coffee.html">here</a>.</p>
<p><a name='fiesta' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="-fiesta-machine-translator-github-com-devonzuegel-fiesta-"><a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/fiesta">Fiesta: Machine Translator</a></h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>March 2015</div><br></div>

<p>Zoe Robert, John Luttig, and I built a Spanish to English machine translator, which we called Fiesta. It is based on the IBM Model 1 algorithm and also implements several Spanish-specific strategies for improving results.</p>
<p>IBM Model 1 is an <strong>expectation-maximization statistical alignment algorithm</strong>. Given known pairings of Spanish and English sentences, it generates a matrix of probabilities whose rows correspond to the Spanish vocabulary and columns correspond to the English vocabulary. The value at any given cell in the matrix represents the probability that those two words have co-occurred within translations of each other. This table is then used to estimate a model for future translations.</p>
<p>In short, IBM Model 1 looks for the most likely English word for a Spanish word (e.g. “dog”) based off our knowledge of co-occurrences within sentences. As such, if there are no translations of a given Spanish word <code>s</code> that contain a given English word <code>e</code>, the value of the cell at the corresponding row and column will be <code>0</code>.</p>
<p>The algorithm requires 3 components:</p>
<ul>
<li>a language model to compute <code>P(E)</code> (the prior)</li>
<li>a translation model to compute <code>P(S|E)</code> (the probability that a Spanish word <code>s</code> translates to an English word <code>e</code>)</li>
<li>a decoder that produces the most probable translation</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="pseudocode">Pseudocode</h4>
<pre class="highlight"><code class="hljs python">initialize transl_prob(e|s) uniformly
do until convergence
  set count(e|s) to <span class="hljs-number">0</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all e,s
  set total_s(s) to <span class="hljs-number">0</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all s
  <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all sentence pairs (en_sentence, sp_sentence)
    set total_e(e) = <span class="hljs-number">0</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all e
    <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all words e <span class="hljs-keyword">in</span> en_sentence
      <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all words s <span class="hljs-keyword">in</span> sp_sentence
        total_e(e) += transl_prob(e|s)
    <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all words e <span class="hljs-keyword">in</span> en_sentence
      <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all words s <span class="hljs-keyword">in</span> sp_sentence
        count(e|s) += transl_prob(e|s) / total_e(e)
        total_s(s) += transl_prob(e|s) / total_e(e)
  <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all s
    <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> all e
      transl_prob(e|s) = count(e|s) / total_s(s)
</code></pre>
<p>You can find the open source code for the project on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/fiesta">Github</a>.</p>
<p><a name='octagon' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="octagon">Octagon</h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>Summer 2014</div><br></div>

<p><img src="http://michaelandassociate.com/fifteen/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/formation8.jpg" alt="right-sm"></p>
<p>This past summer, I designed and built an app called Octagon, a tool for venture capital firms. Octagon helps VCs better manage relationships with portfolio companies by visualizing important metrics about company growth and providing a repository for financial documents and quarterly updates. It also facilitates interaction between investors and board members and the startups in their portfolios in an analogous manner to CRM software. Octagon is currently in beta testing at Formation|8.</p>
<p>I was responsible for the full-stack of the app, though I was lucky enough for the last few weeks of the project to work with a friend named Zack who helped me immensely with the front-end, especially user interaction and fully utilizing the capabilities of our graphing libraries.</p>
<p>You can find the open source code for the project on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/octagon">Github</a>.</p>
<p><a name='paper-trail' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="paper-trail">Paper Trail</h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>March 2014 - present</div><br></div>

<p>Some of the greatest impact individuals can have on politics is driven by daily purchasing decisions. Any time an individual patronizes a corporation, (s)he is fueling the company&#39;s lobbying and donorship capabilities and is indirectly supporting their political causes. Unfortunately, the impact of corporate political contributions is largely opaque to the general public, and the research about corporations’ political activity is a tedious, complex task.</p>
<p>In early 2014, I set out to solve this problem with a project called Paper Trail. The web app provides users access to political profiles of companies and manufacturers. Visualizations and statistics about companies political contributions and lobbying behavior help consumers make informed choices about where their money is going. In turn, consumers&#39; more thoughtful choices empower those corporations that represent their values.</p>
<p>Paper Trail was the first programming project that I pursued outside of class and has evolved significantly since I first implemented it in early 2014. It began as a simple HTML/Javascript app into which users could query the names of companies and learn about their political contributions.</p>
<p>You can find this initial prototype <a href="//stanford.edu/~devonz/paper_trail/about.html">here</a> and the open source code base on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/WWW/tree/master/paper_trail">Github</a>.</p>
<p>Last month, I decided to completely refactor and improve upon Paper Trail with the help of a few friends. We realized that it was unlikely that users would consistently use the app alongside real-life spending, because it would require the tedious process of pulling their phone out of their pocket, typing in the company name, and analyzing the results. We had to find a way to integrate Paper Trail more seamlessly into the users&#39; existing workflow.</p>
<p>We decided that a browser extension would be far more effective than the original idea of a standalone website. Our extension lies on top of Amazon and automatically alerts users of the political activities of the manufacturers of the items in the user&#39;s cart. Beyond solving the problem of relying on users to take action, our new strategy also narrowed our focus to a single site — Amazon — and its users. This had the benefit of leveraging our own experience as Amazon customers, using Amazon&#39;s fantastic API, and generally focusing our energy on specific goals rather than broad ones. </p>
<p>The Paper Trail extension is currently under development. You can find an rough interactive prototype on <a href="//invis.io/SZ1M1F6AJ">Invision</a> and the open source code for the actual extension on <a href="//github.com/devonzuegel/papertrail-extension">Github</a>.</p>
<p><a name='in-other-words' class='anchor' /></p>
<h2 id="in-other-words">In Other Words</h2>
<div class='project-time'><div class='time'>January - May 2011</div><br></div>

<p><img src="http://bookshow.blurb.com/bookshow/cache/P2866696/md/cover_2.jpeg" alt="right-md"></p>
<p>My brother Jeffrey was born with Cerebral Palsy and is on the autistic spectrum. Life with Jeffrey is challenging for both of us because he doesn’t always communicate effectively in the conventional way, in “English.” However, he has found alternative modes with the help of his team of teachers, therapists, family, and friends.</p>
<p>In my junior year in high school, I became fascinated with his growing ability to communicate in non-conventional ways and decided to devote several months to learning more about this process. After conducting extensive interviews and reading further into psychology and cognitive science, I published a documentary book called In Other Words about how he and his team discovers and develops those alternatives.</p>
<p>You can find the book on <a href="http://www.blurb.com/b/2092327-in-other-words">Blurb.com</a>.</p>
]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/pages/projects</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/pages/projects</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 19:29:22 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Public Bus Named Desire]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<!-- img: http://i.imgur.com/B0WjzI5.jpg -->
<p>When I first stumbled across the streetcar vs bus rapid transit (BRT) debate, I was strongly biased towards streetcars. My opinion was largely shaped by the few weeks I spent in Berlin this past summer. While I was in Germany, I relied most heavily on Berlin&#39;s friendly yellow Metrotrams. I really only used the U-bahn and S-bahn when I had to make long, cross-city trips, where the travel time difference was more than 10 or 15 minutes. I used the bus system only once, despite the fact that it was just as extensive as the Metrotram lines.</p>
<p><img src="http://techreleased.techreleased.netdna-cdn.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/28ac57a0085c.jpg" alt="berlin-metrotram"></p>
<p>At the time, I naturally gravitated towards the Metrotrams without consciously considering buses, its main substitute. For all obvious intents and purposes, the bus and metro systems are basically equivalent, so it&#39;s strange that I used one so heavily while all but ignoring the other. I can think of a few reasons why this might have happened:</p>
<ul>
<li>As a first-time visitor to the city with a limited grasp of the German language, I liked the sense of direction the fixed tracks offered. When trying to figure out how to get somewhere, it was nice to see the <strong>rails trailing through the city, clearly marking the Metrotram&#39;s route</strong>.</li>
<li>Somehow the trams <strong>felt more predictable and dependabe</strong> than the buses. This is plainly wrong – bus routes as just as well-defined and stable (at least in the short-term), and all transit options in Berlin run almost perfectly on time (yay for German precision, unlike the Catrain and BART...). My hypothesis is that this perception is another byproduct of the fixed tracks, because they foster <strong>a sense of permanence that boosts the entire system&#39;s credibility</strong>.</li>
<li>I&#39;ve always associated buses with the sketchiest, most obnoxious transit riders. My main exposure to buses has been riding SF&#39;s dingy, smelly cars crushed by mobs of drunk Giants fans and overly talkative tourists. I&#39;m confident in saying that buses have a similar image problem among most middle-class Americans. My <strong>stigmatized perception of buses</strong> governed my transit decisions, despite the fact that Berlin&#39;s buses are actually very clean, and its riders are on the whole very polite.</li>
</ul>
<p>Upon further reflection, I see that streetcars&#39; advantages (as expressed in <a href="http://devonzuegel.com/posts/streetcars-vs-buses-primer">a previous post</a>) all have one trait in common: they are a product of perception. Meanwhile, <strong>buses&#39; advantages are far easier to quantify</strong>. As a result, it is easy for BRT advocates to dismiss streetcars&#39; advantages as petty and unimportant.</p>
<p>I have begrudgingly come to agree that BRT is the way forward; streetcars&#39; modest advantages simply cannot justify their cost. However, rather than dismissing them entirely, <strong>it is critical that planners incorporate streetcars&#39; advantages into BRT systems</strong>. A few ideas for how they could do this:</p>
<div style='float: right; width: 350px; padding: 20px'>
    <img src='http://seattletransitblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/6335549553_26b9e3410a_b.jpg' />

    <img src='https://classes.lt.unt.edu/Fall_2011/CECS_5030_020/aja0029/pictures/dirty%20subway.jpg'/>

    <img src='https://chrissantosra.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/4-seoul-metro-train.jpg?w=611'/>

    <img src='http://www.nikdaum.com/news/osi26.jpg'/>

    <img src='http://nydetailing.com/images/interior-clean-bus.jpg'/>
</div>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Paint bus routes directly onto the streets.</strong> This paint would serve the same function as tram rails running through the city, offering a sense of direction and permanence for a fairly low price.</p>
<div>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Emphasize a clean aesthetic</strong> on both the interior and exterior of the buses. Implement a <strong>zero-tolerance policy for messes</strong>, and design the interior and exterior of the buses with <strong>long-term aesthetics</strong> in mind.</p>
<ul>
<li>All forms of public transit –– but especially buses –– are vulnerable to stigmatization as being dirty and unsafe. Given the sheer volume and diversity of riders, it&#39;s easy to descend below a basic level of sanitation, comfort, and even safety. Any public vehicle quickly devolves into a moving trashcan and graffiti canvas without proper custodial attention. (Never use Caltrain&#39;s onboard bathrooms towards the end of rush hour. Just don&#39;t.) However, this is not inevitable!</li>
<li>Immediate cleanup of messes reminiscent of the <a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/clean-trains/">NYC subway&#39;s zero-tolerance policy</a> for graffiti in the mid 80s could minimize <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_windows_theory">broken windows</a> behavior.<ul>
<li>Riders take far less care with their messes when a space is already dirty, which means that once a vehicle is gross it often spirals down to the depths of disgust until it is finally cleaned. It&#39;s important to keep to cleanliness above that critical threshold to ensure that it doesn&#39;t enter that spiral.</li>
<li>People are less inclined to use transit if it is dirty. This results in thinning out of riders, leaving the space to sketchier characters. I for one feel much more safer riding public transit alongside a large, diverse group of people rather than in a vehicle that is nearly-empty with the exception of one or two sketchy people. This has a cyclical effect –– without a critical mass of reputable-looking individuals, others are less likely to take that form of transit. This leads to a downward spiral of perception as well as actual safety.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Certain materials, colors, and designs are better suited for long-term use. For example, the brushed aluminum seats on the Seoul metro (to the right) are easy to clean and long-lasting, and they&#39;re even shiny! Those cars look like they belong in an industrial kitchen, not an urban transit system. In contrast, seats in many American buses are made of much less durable materials. I have a particularly vivid memory of the buses that hauled my elementary school classes off to various field trips. The seats were outfitted with an ugly vinyl that were brittle and cracked, revealing filthy yellow padding below. A simple choice of more durable, attractive materials would have single-handedly improved my childhood impression of mass transit. (Lucky for the school, we were a captive audience.) If the seats had looked more like the radiant blue of the bus seats pictured to the right, I would have seen mass transit as just another way to get around rather than as a stinky death trap.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>It&#39;s true that none of the benefits of streetcars account for tangible differences. If riders&#39; only goal was to get from point A to point B as fast and cheaply as possible, BRT would categorically sweep streetcars in this debate. However, <strong>riders care about more than just speed and cost; their transit decisions are also influenced by comfort and safety, and they are just as much shaped by perception as the actual experience</strong>.</p>
<p>Streetcars clearly win on this count –– they are just so cute! They harken to an older time, and they feel more permanent and sturdy than buses. <strong>These factors do not outweigh the advantages of BRT, but they should not be ignored.</strong> The perfect system would incorporate the advantages of both options, and there are easy, low-cost steps that could be taken in that direction.</p>
<p>I&#39;d love to hear others&#39; ideas for incorporating the advantages (and cuteness!) of streetcars into BRT systems! Feel free <a href="mailto:devonz@cs.stanford.edu">shoot me an email</a> or <a href="twitter.com/devonzuegel">tweet at me</a> with your thoughts.</p>
]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/posts/a-bus-named-desire</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/posts/a-bus-named-desire</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Devon Zuegel]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 08:17:37 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Automator Workflow to stitch PDFs into a single document]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<!-- img: http://green-romp.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Automator_icon.png -->
<p><img src='../assets/automator-pdf/combine-pdfs.png' width='350px' style='float:right'></p>
<p>I recently made a Mac <a href="../assets/Combine-PDF-Files.workflow.zip">Automator Workflow</a> that allows you to easily stitch together multiple PDFs into a single document. The workflow creates a new PDF while also  To use the workflow on your own computer:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="../assets/automator-pdf/Combine-PDF-Files.workflow.zip">Download</a> the <code>.zip</code> file and extract the workflow from the archive.</li>
<li>When OSX prompts you with &quot;Do you want to install the “Combine PDF Files” service?&quot;, click &quot;Install&quot;.</li>
<li>Navigate to the directory in which the PDFs you wish to combine can be found. Select all of the files at once, and right-click the selection. At the bottom of the menu, click the option called &quot;Combine PDF Files&quot;.</li>
<li>The workflow will ask you to name the new file (including its extension) and to choose its location. Voila!</li>
</ol>
]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/posts/automator-workflow-to-stitch-pdfs-together-into-a-single-document</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/posts/automator-workflow-to-stitch-pdfs-together-into-a-single-document</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Devon Zuegel]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 08:17:43 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An Interview with Dr. Bhattacharya]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="//stanfordreview.org/wp-content/uploads/battacharya.png" alt=""></p>
<p><em>Jay Bhattacharya is an associate professor of Medicine at Stanford and, by courtesy, of Economics. He has been studying the healthcare market for 20 years. He received a BA in economics, an MD and a PhD from Stanford University, where he has taught since 2001.</em> </p>
<h3 id="what-is-the-basic-structure-of-the-affordable-care-act-aca-">What is the basic structure of the Affordable Care Act (ACA)?</h3>
<p>The big context is that there are about 15 to 16 million uninsured people in the US. People view it as a problem, because there’s a lot of financial risk associated with being uninsured, so the ACA aims to expand insurance coverage in two ways. The first is that all people under 138% of the federal poverty line now immediately qualify for Medicaid, while before there were other tests that had to be met. The Congressional Budget Office has said that it’ll cover about 13 million people. The second biggest mechanism is probably these insurance exchanges, which are essentially marketplaces where insurance companies can offer health insurance plans that are regulated by the government.</p>
<p>On top of that basic structure, the ACA puts in place a number of other regulations, the employer and individual mandates being probably the two most well-known. The employer mandate requires all businesses with more than 50 employees to provide health insurance for them. If they don’t, they have to pay a penalty, $2-3 thousand per employee. The individual mandate says that if you don’t have insurance through Medicaid, through your employer, or some other source, then you’re required to buy insurance. If you don’t, they there will be a penalty. I guess the Supreme Court calls it a tax. It amounts to about $700 or 2.5% of your income, whichever is more, per year. So those are the basic coverage provisions of the ACA.</p>
<p>The ACA requires insurance companies to accept all clients, including those with pre-existing conditions. Some experts have voiced concerns about eliminating risk from an inherently-risk based market. What are your thoughts on this subject?</p>
<p>There are also a bunch of provisions that change what qualifies as an insurance product. Among these include things like you have to provide certain kinds of care. There’s an entity called the US Preventative Services Task Force that says if the evidence supports that such-and-such a service is efficacious, then every insurer has to cover it with zero copayment. So for instance, that means that if somebody comes to you, the insurer, and they say, “Hey, I’ve got diabetes, I’ve got heart disease, I’ve got hyper-tension,” you aren’t allowed to say, “No, I won’t insure you.”</p>
<p>The way the insurance companies work is that they look at the predicted health costs of a given risk pool and set their premiums based on that. The ACA provisions make it so that it&#39;s more expensive to cover this pool, because you have to cover more services and riskier people; in turn, the premiums end up being higher. There&#39;s no such thing as a free lunch. You have to pay for these provisions somehow.</p>
<h3 id="the-legislation-only-allows-discrimination-based-on-age-premium-rating-area-family-composition-and-tobacco-use-what-are-the-consequences-of-prohibiting-price-discrimination-based-on-gender-race-and-so-on-and-having-to-offer-the-same-premiums-to-people-of-the-same-age-group-and-geographic-location-">The legislation only allows discrimination based on &quot;age, premium rating area, family composition, and tobacco use.&quot; What are the consequences of prohibiting price discrimination based on gender, race, and so on, and having to offer the same premiums to people of the same age group and geographic location?</h3>
<p>I don&#39;t think you&#39;re constitutionally permitted to price based on race, even though minorities on average tend to have higher health costs. Also, politically, they didn&#39;t want to allow different prices based on gender, even though women tend to have higher health costs than men. Instead, all these groups are pooled together.</p>
<p>This makes insurance look like a better deal for those people who would typically have relatively high health costs. But what that means is that it&#39;ll be much more difficult to get the people with low health costs to sign up, because insurance will look like a bad deal for those people. This is a problem called &quot;adverse selection&quot;, and people are very worried about it in the insurance market, because of these community rating provisions that we&#39;ve been talking about. At least I&#39;m really worried about it.</p>
<p>Even the pricing based on age is greatly restricted. The ACA has defined that the largest ratio for the premiums an insurance company can charge for the oldest and youngest people on their plan is 3:1, while in general it’s usually on the order of 6:1 or 7:1. This is simply because a teenager or college-aged student is on average much less expensive to insure than somebody in their late 60s or 70s. There are all sorts of other restrictions that fall under this umbrella called &quot;community rating laws&quot;, which make it so that people get charged the same premium for health insurance no matter what their risk.</p>
<p>Now this ﻿sounds﻿ good, but it actually has some important negative economic consequences. The first is that -- with a 3:1 ratio -- insurers aren&#39;t going to charge the young an actuarially fair price. Instead, what they&#39;ll charge is a much higher price than the young would normally have to pay for health insurance in order to finance the 3:1 ratio. This is one of the main economic problems caused by the ACA: it makes insurance products on the exchange dependent on recruiting lots of young healthy people, or else the premiums on the market will be extremely high. But in order to recruit these young people, you basically have to threaten them. You have to say, “We&#39;re going to charge you this penalty if you don&#39;t sign up”.</p>
<p>Also, if you&#39;re a “low-income” young person (I&#39;ll tell you what that means in a minute), then you qualify for a subsidy from the federal government to buy insurance on the exchanges. Again, the idea is to induce young people to sign up. So you got the penalty and these subsidies as ways to “incentivize” them to join the exchanges.</p>
<p>So what does “low income” mean? The subsidy scheme goes from 133% (where Medicare ends) to 400% of the poverty line—that’s well into the middle class. For instance, for someone with a family of 5, you can make up to $110 thousand a year and still qualify for money from the federal government to buy insurance on the exchanges. If you&#39;re a single person, then you can make up to $45 thousand per year. That&#39;s a lot of money for a young person to make.</p>
<h3 id="so-how-do-you-expect-this-to-play-out-">So how do you expect this to play out?</h3>
<p>If you&#39;re relatively poor, the exchange subsidies by the federal government are very generous, so a lot of those low-income people will sign up. But if you&#39;re above say 350% of poverty line, you&#39;re relatively healthy and relatively young, it&#39;s actually better for you on average to just pay the penalty. That means that the premiums on the exchange will be much higher than the old individual market, which didn&#39;t have so many of these community rating provisions.</p>
<h3 id="the-individual-mandate-is-one-of-the-most-controversial-parts-of-the-affordable-care-act-on-both-political-and-economic-levels-what-are-your-thoughts-on-this-part-of-the-legislation-">The individual mandate is one of the most controversial parts of the Affordable Care Act on both political and economic levels. What are your thoughts on this part of the legislation?</h3>
<p>The first thing to note is that the individual mandate is absolutely necessary if you have a community rating law. [It’s] an attempt to address the adverse selection problem by essentially forcing people for whom insurance would otherwise be a bad deal to join in. There&#39;s no need for an individual mandate when there&#39;s no adverse selection.</p>
<p>This certainly is a controversial feature, largely because it gives the law this sense of &quot;the government knows better than you do what&#39;s good for you, so they&#39;re going to force you to do it&quot;. A lot of people don&#39;t like that. However, as an economist, I think the results will reflect the financial position that people are in. People will do what&#39;s financially good for them. I think the key thing to look at is: who&#39;s going to benefit and who&#39;s going to lose?</p>
<h3 id="are-those-people-who-wouldn-t-be-buying-health-insurance-if-it-weren-t-for-the-individual-mandate-the-losers-">Are those people who wouldn’t be buying health insurance if it weren’t for the individual mandate the “losers”?</h3>
<p>Well those aren&#39;t the only losers, though they certainly are losers. Another group are those people who have existing insurance on the individual market—many of them have been receiving cancellation letters, because their insurance plans don’t meet the requirements of the ACA. So because they don&#39;t meet those, the ACA considers them as &quot;bad insurance&quot;. The people who had that insurance, though, considered it good insurance! They were paying for the things they wanted, not the things the government--in particular the ACA--thinks they ought to have.</p>
<h3 id="the-affordable-care-act-is-complex-and-it-can-be-intimidating-to-try-to-make-sense-of-how-it-will-impact-the-typical-american-do-you-see-this-complexity-as-a-potential-weakness-of-the-legislation-">The Affordable Care Act is complex, and it can be intimidating to try to make sense of how it will impact the typical American. Do you see this complexity as a potential weakness of the legislation?</h3>
<p>It&#39;s a very difficult system. It&#39;s something like one-sixth of the US economy, with different actors with different points of view-- doctors, hospitals, insurers, individuals, employers. Basically every facet of domestic life is touched by this legislation. So if you&#39;re going to do this sort of legislation, I don&#39;t see how you could do it without a complex set of regulations. The question is &quot;Is it wise to do it this way?&quot; or &quot;Are there other, simpler ways to do it?&quot;</p>
<p>The administration has often oversimplified and, in some places, directly misled the American public about what the likely effects of this legislation are. The most famous example is President Obama&#39;s promise that “if you like your insurance then you can keep it.” It was clear from the very beginning, based on the structure of the law, that that wasn&#39;t going to be true.</p>
<p>A big ticket item is that the employer mandate was due to go into effect in January 2014, but the administration delayed it a year. And there are a couple of reasons I think they did that, though none of these are the official reasons they gave. The ACA defines &quot;affordable&quot; as the value of 9.5% or less of your income. So if you make $100k, an affordable plan would be $9500. For a young person with that income, that would actually be a very, very expensive health plan. For me, with a family of 5, a $9500 plan would be a very cheap plan. On average, families pay about $17k per year for insurance, while to cover a single person costs about $5 thousand per year.</p>
<p>Now, any company with more than 50 full-time employees has to offer them affordable insurance. The technical problem is that...suppose you have a worker who comes to the insurance exchange and says &quot;Look, I only make 200% of the poverty line, and my employer isn&#39;t offering me insurance coverage” -- the federal government is then supposed to give that worker a whole bunch of money so they can go buy insurance on the exchange, but at least in principle they ought to check with the employer to make sure the employer actually doesn&#39;t offer that guy a plan. And it&#39;s technically a very difficult problem, because currently there&#39;s no reporting by employers. The ACA requires reporting, but it&#39;s been difficult to get that system going in a centralized way.</p>
<p>But there&#39;s also a second, very important economic reason that has gone too unnoticed. If the employer gives you an &quot;affordable&quot; health plan, then you don&#39;t qualify for the subsidies, even if you&#39;re low income on the exchange. The way they define affordability is based on a price of health insurance for a single person. Imagine you have a family of 4 or 5, and your employer offers you a plan for a single person that&#39;s $5 thousand—well under 9.5% your income—they also give you an option to cover your entire family for $16 thousand. Well that&#39;s ﻿not﻿ &quot;affordable&quot;, since it&#39;s more than 9.5% of your income. What that means is that if you get insurance coverage for yourself but not your family, you can get that relatively cheaply from your employer. But then your family&#39;s not covered. However, when they go to the exchange to get insurance, they don’t qualify for federal subsidies, because technically you’re all covered by your employer. This creates all kinds of strange incentives. For instance, if the husband and wife got a divorce, the family then qualifies for exchange subsidies, even if they don&#39;t change any behavior other than they get divorced.</p>
<p>But the more common thing that&#39;s likely to happen is that a lot of employers will just drop coverage and pay the penalty, and it&#39;ll actually be better for the workers, too, especially if they are low-income. If their employer drops insurance, they can then raise wages, and the workers will still qualify for federal subsidies on the exchange. It&#39;s a win-win for workers and employers. I&#39;ve done a published calculation (content.healthaffairs.org/content/32/9/1531.abstract) where I found that for 37 million employees who currently get insurance, it&#39;s financially beneficial for their employer to drop coverage for them. It&#39;s also financially beneficial for the worker. But there&#39;s no such thing as a free lunch-- we say that it&#39;s good for the employers, it&#39;s good for the employees, but it’s bad for taxpayers. The estimates of the costs of the law are way lower than what they ultimately will be, because they don&#39;t sufficiently account for the economic benefit to workers and employers of dropping coverage, especially for employees.</p>
<h3 id="what-are-the-economic-effects-of-requiring-insurance-packages-to-include-certain-provisions-and-coverage-for-example-birth-control-">What are the economic effects of requiring insurance packages to include certain provisions and coverage, for example birth control?</h3>
<p>In general, it raises the premiums-- the more things that are covered, the more that you have to charge to be able to pay the costs. If you&#39;re not paying it in the copay, then you&#39;re paying it in the premium. Nothing is free.</p>
<p>The ACA requires insurers to extend dependent coverage to adult children up to 26 years old. Do you think this is going to have a net positive effect to those children or over time it&#39;ll cause the premiums to rise?</p>
<p>Before, it was only kids under 21 who were covered as dependents under most family insurance plans. What it&#39;s done is it&#39;s raised the premiums for insurance for parents who have kids from 21 and 26. It&#39;s parents continuing to pay for the kids’ insurance. Again, it&#39;s not ﻿free﻿ coverage. So that&#39;s one effect-- it&#39;s raised the premiums for parents. The second thing is that it deprives the individual market of young, healthy people who could potentially pool with the sicker people. A 23-year-old who&#39;s covered by their parents has no incentive to go buy insurance in the exchange market. They don&#39;t have to pay a penalty, because they&#39;re already covered. What that means is that there&#39;s one fewer young, healthy person to pool with the older, sicker people on the exchange, making the adverse selection problem that we talked about earlier worse.</p>
]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/posts/an-interview-with-dr-bhattacharya</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/posts/an-interview-with-dr-bhattacharya</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Devon Zuegel]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2015 07:00:19 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Batch installing fonts in multiple subdirectories]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<!-- img: http://i.stack.imgur.com/o76m6.png -->
<p>I&#39;m a digital pack rat, especially when it comes to fonts. Every time I see a nice typeface, I immediately forget whatever it is I&#39;m actually reading and instead dig into the source code, find its name, and search the corners of the web for a a free copy. It doesn&#39;t help that my favored form of procrastination is scrolling through pages upon pages of fonts on sites like <a href="https://www.myfonts.com/">MyFonts.com</a> and <a href="http://www.fontsquirrel.com/">FontSquirrel.com</a>. The result is that I frequently find myself with a mess of directories bloated with <code>.ttf</code> and <code>.otf</code> files. <img src='http://i.imgur.com/VTK3tEG.png' width='270px' style='float:right; margin:15px'/></p>
<p>The sad hangover to my embarrassingly frequent font binges is actually installing them. OSX has no easy way to get multiple fonts into Font Book all at once, leaving you with the painful task of installing them by hand, one by one. It&#39;s particularly unpleasant when the files are in multiple subfolders, the common format of the downloaded bundles I love so much.</p>
<p>Luckily, it&#39;s easy to install all fonts within the subfolders of a directory from the command line with the following steps:</p>
<ol>
<li><p>First, <strong>locate the parent directory</strong> of all of the font files you wish to install. In my case, the directory is <code>~/Downloads/fonts-to-install</code>.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Next, <strong>open your terminal</strong> and <strong>enter the following command</strong> to install the fonts directly into Font Book. If you are dealing with <code>.otf</code> s or some other file type, replace <code>&quot;*.ttf&quot;</code> with <code>&quot;*.otf&quot;</code>.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<pre class="highlight"><code class="hljs bash">find ~/Downloads/fonts-to-install\ Fonts/ -name <span class="hljs-string">"*.ttf"</span> -exec cp -iv {} /Library/Fonts \;
</code></pre>
<p>And that&#39;s that! Go use your newly-saved font-installing time for something fun.</p>
]]></description>
            <link>http://devonzuegel.com/posts/batch-installing-fonts-in-multiple-subfolders</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://devonzuegel.com/posts/batch-installing-fonts-in-multiple-subfolders</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Devon Zuegel]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 08:17:50 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>